<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief history of the pious and glorious life and actions of the most illustrious princess, Mary Queen of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, &amp;c. Containing the most memorable things, and matters, relating to her royal self, &amp;c. from her birth till the most deplorable time of her ever to be lamented death, on the 28th. of December, 1694. Faithfully done by J.S.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93564</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S46</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230766</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896476</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896476</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154343</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93564)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154343)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2412:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief history of the pious and glorious life and actions of the most illustrious princess, Mary Queen of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, &amp;c. Containing the most memorable things, and matters, relating to her royal self, &amp;c. from her birth till the most deplorable time of her ever to be lamented death, on the 28th. of December, 1694. Faithfully done by J.S.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
                  <author>Drapentier, Jan, fl. 1674-1713, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 134, [2] p., : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Gwillim, in Bishopsgate-street, and sold by most booksellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Portrait of Queen Mary signed: J. Drapentier sculpcit.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary --  II, --  Queen of England, 1662-1694 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1660-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Queen Mary</figDesc>
                  <byline>J. Drapentier Sculpeit</byline>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QUI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <head>Mary Queen of England Scotland France &amp; Ireland Defender of the Faith &amp;c Obit Dece. 28 1694 Etate Sua 32.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF HISTORY OF THE Pious and Glorious LIFE and ACTIONS OF THE Moſt Illuſtrious Princeſs, MARY <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING The moſt Memorable Things, and Matters, relating to Her <hi>Royal Self, &amp;c.</hi> from Her BIRTH till the moſt Deplorable time of Her ever to be Lamented DEATH, on the <hi>28th.</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> 1694.</p>
            <p>Faithfully Done by <hi>J. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Gwillim,</hi> in <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreet;</hi> and Sold by moſt Bookſellers, 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WHEN we undertake a Work of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the weight of ſo Illuſtrious a Subject ought to ſtrike us not only with awe and reverence, but make us Conſider, in the moſt ſerious manner, how we proceed in it, when, indeed, the moſt Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Pens in <hi>Europe,</hi> may come ſhort of the Worth and Luſtre of ſo Pious and Renowned a <hi>Princeſs,</hi> whoſe Fame may be ſaid to have Travelled with the Sun; and whoſe Virtues ſhall ſtand a living Monument to all
<pb facs="tcp:154343:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ages, when Tombs of Marble, and ſtately Piramids are eaten by time, or crumbled into Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins. Her Renown ſhall be freſh in the minds of Men whilſt the world laſts, and then paſſing beyond time, ſhall have Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nety in ſtore; till then Like a guiding Star, Her Great Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may direct our Lives in ways of Piety, and be held truly to deſerve that part o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her Royal Title, that ſtiled he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Defender of the Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THAT She was the beſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Queen</hi>'s, the Mourning Nation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tears do ſadly expreſs in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Loſs: And the Royal Sorrow of a Grieving Monarch, declare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Her the beſt of Wives. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore as her worth was exceedin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great, ſo her loſs is unexpreſſibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to us, though to her, paſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:154343:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Peradveuture, the Gain is as Excellent and Glorious, in a happy State, as Changing an Earthly, for a Heavenly Crown can render it.</p>
            <p>BUT to come ſome what nearer to the purpoſe of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Hiſtory. The Reader may find in it, all that is Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and worthy in the Perſon and Character of a <hi>Queen,</hi> who made it her endeavour, through the Series of her Life, to give a worthy Example to her People; and leave a Fame behind Her, of being Her Sex's Glory and Wonder: Who' like the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Induſtriouſly laboured for the Nations good, eſpecially in the ſupport and encouragement of that beſt part of Government, which procures
<pb facs="tcp:154343:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Gods Favours and Bleſſings on all the other parts, <hi>viz. The true Religion in the Purity of Worſhip,</hi> as She found it Eſtabliſhed, and had perſevered in from her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy: Rejoycing only in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, and promoting thoſe that made Piety their brighteſt Ornament: ſo that Her Pallace ſeem'd a Temple, where Virtue &amp; unfeigned Devotion flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Her Cloſet a place fit for Angels to Viſit and Admire, with Holy Joy and Reſpect: So that Her Actions leave no room for Flattery, being all Centered in that Merrit which Tranſcends ſuch meanneſs that might at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on other Women, and flow from Mercinary Pens, to ſet them off with borrowed Luſter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>BUT not to Detain you longer, from that which may prove yet more pleaſing to all True <hi>Engliſh</hi> Spirits, we ſhall only add, That what is Inſerted in this ſmall Vollum, is Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the moſt Exact and Certain Truths, Carefully Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and Comprized in a Method ſuitable to ſo Illuſtrious a Theme.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>VALE.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154343:7"/>
            <head>A BRIEF HISTORY OF THE Pious and Glorious LIFE and ACTIONS OF THE Moſt Illuſtrious Princeſs, MARY <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WHEN with our Pens we approach <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and undertake to Write the Actions of Illuſtrious Perſons, who deſervedly command a Character ſuitable to their Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, we ought to move with ſuch caution and care, that haſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedneſs will not permit of: There is a kind of Veneration due, &amp; therefore the Ballance ought to be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154343:8"/>poifed with all the juſtneſs and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs imaginable; or like thoſe that raiſe a ſtately Fabrick, lay a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation ſuitable to the intended Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructure, Expreſs it in ſuch Words and Truths, as may <hi>put gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers to Silence,</hi> or convince preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced Perſons (if any ſuch there be) of their Errors: And if ever a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> of a ſublime Nature, preſt the Pens of Men, to Celebrate a Memory worthy to be Character'd in Gold and Crown'd with Stars, we here (though in Sorrow for the Worlds eneſtimable loſs) have found it; and with humble ſubmiſſion ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, with willingneſs, however weak and defficient our endeavours may prove; and labour to pay a Tribute due to one, whoſe high De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts and wonderous Excellencies, expreſs themſelves in a livelineſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Eloquence of the ſmootheſt Oratory, or the frame of Words can utter: Though Tears or Grief, after ſuch a Loſs, would let them flow
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154343:8"/>with all the Sweetneſs Rhetoritions can model or contrive.</p>
            <p>THE Queen! That very Name gives ſcope to thoughts, and delates them like expanded Gold: But when with that Name, Her Virtues are conſider'd, we find them bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs or unlimited; and our ſelves at a loſs to bring them to Center in ſuitable expreſſions.</p>
            <p>THIS Great <hi>Princeſs,</hi> ſo long the Joy of Three Kingdoms, and the Peoples Bleſſing, Deſcended by the Fathers ſide, from a long Race of Princes, that ſway'd the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Scepter; Memorable in Hiſtory for great Actions; and Renown'd at Home and Abroad. She was Eldeſt Daughter to the Late King <hi>James,</hi> by his firſt Wife <hi>Ann,</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>York,</hi> Daughter to the Earl of <hi>Clar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endon.</hi> She was Born at the Royal Pallace of St. <hi>James</hi>'s, on the <hi>30th.</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1662. when the Nations Joy was arriv'd at an Extraordinary height, for the Settlement and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154343:9"/>it found under the eaſie Government of a Reſtor'd King, (<hi>viz.</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second.) Which Joy was yet more encreaſed. by the Birth of an Illuſtrious <hi>Princeſs,</hi> that in her Infancy gave hopes of thoſe great and Glorious things, that have been ſince manifeſted to the World.</p>
            <p>THIS happy News being ſoon ſpread through the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, great were the Congratulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Joy, Bells Ringing every where, and Bonfires and Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were in all Remarkable Places; and many Rich Preſents, by the Nobles and Ladys at Court, were made to the Royal Infant. And She was Chriſtened according to the Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and, after her <hi>Royal Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother,</hi> Named <hi>MARY.</hi> Tended and Nurs'd ſhe was with great care, in the moſt Royal manner. And as God gave her a Beautiful Shape and Countinance, to which were added,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154343:9"/>a Pomp of winning Graces, even in her tender Years, ſo he was pleaſed to continue towards her, a Health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Conſtitution of Body, for the moſt part; and Endowed her with an Aire and Livelyneſs beyond thoſe of her Years.</p>
            <p>BUT not to inſiſt upon her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, when ſhe was in her Cradle; we find ſhe was no ſooner capable of Education, but King <hi>Charles</hi> her Uncle, <hi>(of Bleſſed Memory)</hi> took care ſhe ſhould be Educated in the <hi>Proteſtant Religion, as Eſtabliſhed in the Church of England.</hi> Which Royal Care, ſuited extreamly with her Own Inclination; and having <hi>Tutors</hi> appointed to Inſtruct her in all that is good and Princely, ſo far as the Capacity of her Years would admit, She was Grounded in that Religion and thoſe Virtues, that have rendred her a Bleſſing to theſe Nations, and made her a Pattern to all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages; and Her Loſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to be Deplor'd and Lamented.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:154343:10"/>
            <p>HER Abhorrence of the <hi>Romiſh Superſtitions,</hi> and the Cruelties of that <hi>Bloody Church,</hi> was very early Imbibed; which made Her not only keep at a diſtance Her Self, but labour to prevent others from Wading into thoſe Errors, by her Perſwaſions and Favours.</p>
            <p>THE Scripture, as ſoon as She had Learn'd well to Read, She made Her Delight. She Frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Chappel</hi> upon all Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys, and Solemn Occaſions that Offered; and was Extraordinary Attentive to the <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and very Fervent in her own Devotions: Heeding but little the Paſtimes and Pleaſures that then were at Height in the Court. And though being a <hi>Princeſs</hi> of Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, and in a ſtation of Eminency, yet She carry'd Her Self with that Courteous Obliging Modeſty, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Her Inferious, that Won Her a Place in their Hearts, that could not be taken up by any other, or ever Obliterated.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:154343:10"/>
            <p>THIS Early Sprouting of <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> in the beſt of Princeſſes, was only as a <hi>Prodrom</hi> or <hi>Forerunner</hi> of an enlargement of Excellent things; as the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Streaks of Light, foretelling the Riſing of the <hi>Sun,</hi> to Refreſh the World with Kindly Heat; and Render it <hi>Gay</hi> and <hi>Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> in its Fragrancy and Fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>THIS made Queen <hi>Catharine,</hi> her Royal <hi>Aunt,</hi> highly Love and Eſteem her, as a <hi>Jewel in Nature,</hi> Admiring her <hi>Virtue,</hi> (though ſhe differed from her in Opinion, as to <hi>Religion.</hi>) And indeed, ſeeing that King <hi>Charles</hi> had not any Iſſue by his Queen, the Eyes of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were upon this Illuſtrious <hi>Princeſs,</hi> as a Flouriſhing <hi>Branch,</hi> proceeding from the <hi>Royal Stem.</hi> Under whoſe Shaddowing Protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, we have ſince ſat ſecure, till our Grief diſturbed us, by Her Changing this Life for One more Glorious.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:154343:11"/>
            <p>HER <hi>Charity,</hi> even in Her ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Years, was not only great to the <hi>Poor,</hi> in hard and neceſſitous Times, but ſhe ſtired up others, by her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citements, to Imitate her <hi>Pious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</hi> which is ſo great an Ornament to the <hi>Chriſtian Religion;</hi> and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died how ſhe might beſt diſpoſe of her <hi>Royal Bounties,</hi> to thoſe that ſtood moſt in need of them. Cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Enquiry to be made for Poor, Decay'd, Suffering <hi>Houskeepers</hi> and <hi>Orphans,</hi> that were by the Death of their <hi>Parents,</hi> expos'd to a deſperate Fortune; and there her ſeaſonable Relief came. Which made the Souls of the <hi>Hungry</hi> Bleſs her; and ſend up Prayers to Almighty God for ſo worthy a Benefactoreſs.</p>
            <p>SHE was about Nine Years of Age when the firſt Afflicting Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row came near her Heart, for the Death of her Illuſtrious Mother, <hi>Ann</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>York:</hi> Who, after a long Indiſpoſition, at her Pallace of St <hi>James</hi>'s, in the County of <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:154343:11"/>Dyed on the <hi>31ſt.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> Greatly Lamented of the whole Nation, but Eſpecially of this Pious <hi>Princeſs,</hi> whoſe Tender Heart found then the firſt touches of Sorrow, for the Loſs of ſo Kind and Indulgent a Mother: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, this Great <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> was a Happy Providence to theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, whoſe Fruitful Womb Bleſt us with Two Proteſtant Princeſſes, Matchleſs for <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Virtue;</hi> and thoſe Excellent Graces that Adorn the <hi>Sex.</hi> To one of which, next to God, and our Gracious Soveraign, we are Beholden to for our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, from an Inundation of many Miſeries, that Threaten'd us from a Party that have all along Labour'd to Undermine the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church and Government.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Court</hi> upon the <hi>Death</hi> of this Great Lady, went into Deep <hi>Mourning,</hi> and the <hi>Funeral Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys,</hi> were performed with all the Decency, and Solemn Pomp, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154343:12"/>ſuited her High Degree, after ſhe had brought into the World Three <hi>Princes,</hi> and Three <hi>Princeſſes,</hi> Viz.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Charles</hi> her Firſt Son, who was Created Duke of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Born the Firſt of <hi>January,</hi> 1660. Who Dyed at <hi>Richmond</hi> the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> 1667.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Princeſs <hi>MARY,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our Gracious Queen, the Principal Subject of this Hiſtory, the Time and Place of whoſe Birth, is already mentioned.</p>
            <p n="3">III. A Second Son, Born on the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1663, and Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>James</hi> on the <hi>22d.</hi> of the ſame Month, and Created Duke of <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale.</hi> Who Dyed at St. <hi>James</hi>'s the <hi>26th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1667.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Of a Third Son, on <hi>July</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> 1666.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Of a Second Daughter, on the <hi>13th</hi> of <hi>January</hi> 1668. Who was on the <hi>15th</hi> of that Month Chriſtned <hi>Heneretta,</hi> and Dyed, at
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154343:12"/>St. <hi>James</hi>'s on the <hi>15th</hi> of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1669.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Of another Daughter, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Named <hi>Ann,</hi> now Her Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Highneſs, the Princeſs of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND here though we take a Sad and Melancholy Survey of the Loſs of ſo many Princes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in their Infancy, yet God was aboundant in his Mercys, in preſerving the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Luſtre of the Royal Family, to make the Nation Amends, for thoſe Happy Souls he had ſo timely taken to himſelf, from a Trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome World to a more Happy State, in Joys that far Tranſcend the Value of all Earthly Crowns.</p>
            <p>FROM this ſadneſs that Afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Spirits of a Young Princeſs, that ſhe might be averted, and draw in Comforts to Chear and Enliven her Drooping Spirits, ſhe was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at Divers <hi>Maſques,</hi> and <hi>Balls,</hi> held at <hi>Court,</hi> ſo ſoon as the time of the General <hi>Mourning</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154343:13"/>over, and would Decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admit of Mirth to Diſſipate the Clouds of Sadneſs that hung about it. And not long after, the <hi>Duke</hi> after the Loſs of his <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought himſelf of a Second Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and Pitched upon <hi>Mary,</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Modena</hi>'s Daughter, which Negotiation, was oppoſed by the Parliament, then ſitting. Yet, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their endeavours to avert it, and place his Mind on a <hi>Proteſtant Princeſs,</hi> The Marriage by <hi>Proxie</hi> was concluded, and on the <hi>21ſt</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> 1673, She and her Mother Arrived at <hi>Dover,</hi> On Board the Ship appointed for their Equipage; and ſoon after the Marriage was Solemnized, with little Pomp, becauſe it ſeemed not greatly pleaſing to the Nation.</p>
            <p>THE Illuſtrious Princeſs <hi>Marys</hi> Reſentments on this Match, we do not undertake to determine; tho' we do not think, a Lady of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Religion, and different In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154343:13"/>could be much pleaſing to her, yet ſuch was her Generous Temper, that ſhe choſe rather to keep her thoughts in the Sacred Cabinet of her Pious Breaſt, than to utter them, and when on the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>January</hi> 1675, the New <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> was brought to Bed of a Daughter, at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, at the Splendid <hi>Chriſtening</hi> of this Infant, the Princeſs <hi>Mary,</hi> and her Siſter, the Princeſs <hi>Ann,</hi> were to ſtand <hi>Godmothers,</hi> and the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> was <hi>Godfather.</hi> The Child was <hi>Chriſtned, Catharina Laura,</hi> but Lived not any conſiderable time after.</p>
            <p>And now our Pious <hi>Princeſs,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Inſtitutions of the Church ſhe was Baptiſed into, and that after being Baptiſed, Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when we come to more Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Years, is requiſite, She and the Lady <hi>Ann</hi> were Confirmed at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> by the <hi>Dean</hi> of the <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> with the uſual <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154343:14"/>all the Devotions that is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on ſo Solemn Occaſion.</p>
            <p>KING <hi>Charles</hi> ſoon after this, deſirous to prefer his Illuſtrious <hi>Neices</hi> to <hi>Proteſtant Princes,</hi> for the ſecurity of our <hi>Religion,</hi> and the welfare of the Kingdom; ſeeing he had no Iſſue by <hi>Donna Catharina</hi> his Queen: Refuſing all others pitch'd upon the Illuſtrious <hi>Prince of Orange.</hi> A Prince Deſcended from one of the Greateſt, and moſt Nobleſt Houſes in <hi>Europe;</hi> whoſe Anceſtors have Signaliz'd their Conduct and Courage like <hi>Heroes</hi> and <hi>Worthys;</hi> and thereby Riveted their Names to <hi>Eternity,</hi> and leſt a grateful Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory to all Poſterity; as being the <hi>Liberators</hi> of the Opreſſed, and the often Confirmers of the Peace of <hi>Europe:</hi> Setling the moſt thriving and proſperous States in the World; and what is more, Mantained it, from its Infancy, againſt Opreſſors. But, as if all their Virtues and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage had centered in this <hi>Prince,</hi> (our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154343:14"/>moſt Gracious Soveraign) the Wonders He has done, comprize, and in a higher meaſure do exceed, their many Great Exploits. But to come nearer to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The Fair and Virtuous <hi>Princeſs</hi> having been ſeen by this Illuſtrious <hi>Prince,</hi> when he was in <hi>England,</hi> to Viſit his Royal Relations, Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1670 So much Virtue and Innocent Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, no doubt made ſome impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on his Mind, to conſider, and eſteem her above all other <hi>Princeſſes</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> as were not Obliterated, by the ſpaces of time, that inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven'd between that and the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py joining of their Hands, in the Sacred Marriage Ties, that brought ſo great a Bleſſing to theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and to ſhow what high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem the Nation had then of a <hi>Prince,</hi> whoſe Virtues early Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, and whoſe Fame was Loud in <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Camps,</hi> for <hi>Prudent</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:154343:15"/>Councils and <hi>Martial Deeds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>Lord-Mayor, and Court of Aldermen,</hi> on the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> (after his Arival, and having been <hi>Careſſed</hi> by the Court, and Obliged with all the <hi>Splendid Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment</hi> it could afford) Waited upon him, to Welcome him to <hi>England,</hi> and on the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> he did them the Honour to <hi>Dine</hi> with them at <hi>Drapers-Hall,</hi> where he was highly <hi>Congratulated,</hi> and ſplendidly <hi>Entertained,</hi> and by the Shouts and Acclamations of the people, the <hi>Citys Genious</hi> ſeem'd then to Bend to him, as a Fortunate preſage of the deliverance ſhe might expect from him in her greateſt diſtreſſes, and after found Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>City</hi> having expreſſed their Joy to be Honoured in the preſence of ſo Illuſtrious a <hi>Prince,</hi> of the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Stem, the <hi>Vniverſity</hi> of <hi>Oxford</hi> (the <hi>Seed-Plat</hi> of <hi>Learning,</hi> and <hi>Virtuous Education,</hi> from whence
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154343:15"/>chiefly ſtreams, thoſe Pious <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> that by their unwearied endeavours, make <hi>Religion</hi> Flouriſh among us) was Graced by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. For going from the <hi>Court</hi> to <hi>Windſor,</hi> he took his way from thence, and was received by the <hi>Heads</hi> of the <hi>Colledges</hi> in their <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities,</hi> and, being highly Treated, took a view of all that is <hi>Rare</hi> and <hi>Curious,</hi> in that Antient <hi>City. &amp;c.</hi> And was pleaſed (as a mark of the Satisfaction he received) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of a <hi>Degree;</hi> and ſo returning to <hi>London,</hi> on the <hi>23d</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> he there kept his <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> in the nigheſt Splendor the <hi>Court</hi> was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of performing. And on the <hi>13th</hi> of <hi>February</hi> took his leave of the <hi>King, Duke,</hi> and <hi>Princeſſes,</hi> in order to his <hi>Return</hi> to <hi>Holland,</hi> where he happily Ariv'd, with a Fair Wind, in a few days.</p>
            <p>HE was <hi>Congratulated</hi> upon his Return by the <hi>States General,</hi> and thief <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> of His Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:154343:16"/>
            <p>AS we have before hinted, after this happy interview, King <hi>Charles</hi> bending his mind to bring about a Match, which proved grateful to the greateſt part of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> he ſent Divers <hi>Engliſh</hi> Noblemen, to Invite him over a ſecond time, who found him in <hi>Arms</hi> amidſt his Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, repelling the <hi>Armys</hi> of the Invader, and Diſturber of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>AND having delivered their Welcome Meſſage, finding, without great diſadvantage, he could not oblige the <hi>French</hi> to a Battle, he drew near with his <hi>Army</hi> to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and leaving the charge of it (aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter neceſſary Orders were given') to Count <hi>Waldeck,</hi> went to the <hi>Hague;</hi> and having received the thanks of the <hi>States,</hi> for his Prudent Conduct of their <hi>Army,</hi> he Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued for <hi>England,</hi> with thoſe <hi>Nobles</hi> that had attended him by the <hi>Kings</hi> Order, and divers of his own Nation, in the <hi>Yatches</hi> that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154343:16"/>were ſent to attend him, with Three <hi>Men of War,</hi> and a Squadron of <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships, Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him by the <hi>States, commanded</hi> by Admiral <hi>Evertſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SETTING out with a Proſperous Gale, they Arived at <hi>Harwich</hi> on the 19 of <hi>October,</hi> 1677. Where the Duke of <hi>Albermarle</hi> ſent by the <hi>King</hi> to that intent, waited upon him to Congratulate his Arival; as did livers of the <hi>Kings</hi> Coaches: And ſo he proceeded to <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> where the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Duke,</hi> attended with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Splendid Train of Nobility, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him; and Congratulated, not only his Arival, but Glorious Succeſſes abroad. And ſo, in the moſt Magnificent Manner, they proceeded to <hi>London;</hi> and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> with unexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able demonſtrations of Joy; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad the pleaſure again, to ſee the Faireſt Flower in <hi>Englands</hi> Garden; which now appeared more Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Lovely, no doubt, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154343:17"/>by reaſon of her more Matur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Years, but becauſe Heaven ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Deſtin'd her to be his <hi>Royal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort,</hi> to make him a partner in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Faithful and Tranſcendant Love that exceeded what before or ſine has been known, or exampled o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Earth.</p>
            <p>NO ſooner was this intende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> match ſpread abroad by Fame, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Nations joy ſwelled to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible height, and over-flowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Bounds of Moderation: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> willing and wiſhing People though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that time moved too flow, till th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> happy day of its appointed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumation Dawn'd, to Bleſs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Land with its Welcome Light.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>King,</hi> on the Firſt of <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> having declared his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the <hi>Council,</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> extreamly pleaſed and ſatisfied wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, as well in the Merrits of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Worthy and Juſt a <hi>Prince,</hi> as in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſecurity they expected (from ſo a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greeable a Marriage) of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154343:17"/>Religion.</hi> And to teſtify how well they reſented it, delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to go in a Body, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate the <hi>Princeſs,</hi> upon the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py occaſion of her being about to enter into a State of <hi>Matrimony,</hi> with ſo Illuſtrious a <hi>Husband:</hi> As by their Example did moſt of the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters of State:</hi> Declaring the high ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction they conceived in it, and expected from it; who had very Gratious and Obliging returns of thanks for their kindneſs, and good opinion of it.</p>
            <p>ALL things being agreed on, in order to this <hi>Bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> by Expreſs, ſent the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> an account of his Proceedings, the Subſtance of it being to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>THAT in Conſideration it had been their earneſt deſires, and requeſt to him, to ſee him Marryed, when he had well weighed the reaſons that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154343:18"/>him to it, in a Conformity t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Wiſhes and Deſires; and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tranquility of their</hi> State, <hi>he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived he could not do better, than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Addreſs himſelf to the Princeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> MARY, Eldeſt Daughter to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Duke of York: <hi>That he had made it his Requeſt to have her in Marriage both of the</hi> King <hi>and the</hi> Duke, <hi>who had not refuſed, but condeſcended to his requeſt, and propoſals; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thought it requiſite, to give their</hi> Lordſhips <hi>an account of it; expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Return, their ſpeedy Approbation, that he might the ſooner return to them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>THEY had no ſooner received this Advice, with the Higheſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction imaginable, but they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately aſſembled to conſult a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and conſider the weighty rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that obliged the <hi>Prince</hi> to make ſo agreeable a choice, to make them happy, in placing his affections on the moſt Virtuous and Celebrated <hi>Princeſs,</hi> in <hi>Europe;</hi> approving it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154343:18"/>with Congratulation and joy, and made the high ſatisfaction they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived known by a publick <hi>Edict,</hi> declaring their good opinion and eſteem of ſo great an Alliance; promiſing not only to reſpect, but to obſerve it to the utmoſt: And further, to teſtify their conſent, they ſent their <hi>Approbation</hi> on the Fourth of <hi>November,</hi> to the <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THINGS being Happily brought to this paſs, and all things being prepared for the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Marriage, it was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Day the <hi>States Approbation</hi> Arived, being the <hi>Prince</hi>'s Birth-Day: The <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>London</hi> Tying this Happy Knot of <hi>Wedlock,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the apointed <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> preſenting the <hi>Royal Bride.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE News of this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> was ſounded aloud, through the Three Kingdoms, by <hi>Ringing of Bells,</hi> and <hi>Joyful Acclamations</hi> of the People, with <hi>Bonfires,</hi> and other <hi>Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:154343:19"/>The <hi>Gentry</hi> and <hi>Nobility</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving very plentifully to the Poor. And the Royal Pair received the Congratulations of the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perſons of the Nation; having been before entertained in the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> at the <hi>Annual Inveſture</hi> of the <hi>Lord-Mayor,</hi> on his being Sworn before the <hi>Barrons</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> Divers Congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory <hi>Poems</hi> were made by the beſt hands, Illuſtrating upon a Subject that was before very Glorious in the Eyes of the Nation.</p>
            <p>AFTER ſome few Days ſpent at <hi>Court,</hi> in Feaſting and Royal <hi>Treatments,</hi> of <hi>Balls</hi> and <hi>Muſick,</hi> and <hi>Songs of Triumph;</hi> having farther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Complements of the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> and <hi>Chief Miniſters of State,</hi> the Royal Pair, on the <hi>29th,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for <hi>Holland,</hi> took their leave, attended with a Train of <hi>Noblemen</hi> and <hi>Ladies,</hi> Embarqued in the <hi>Yatches,</hi> and waited on by divers <hi>Men of War,</hi> order'd to that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154343:19"/>purpoſe, Sailed with a Proſperous Gail, and Landed at <hi>Ter-Hyde:</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from thence to <hi>Hounſlery-Dyke,</hi> where they continued for ſome time, and received private viſits, till things could be prepared for a Reception ſuitable to their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters at the <hi>Hague.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THINGS being prepared in the moſt Splendid manner, upon their approach they were met by Divers Nobles; and found the Bridge Crowned with Garlands, and Twelve Companys of <hi>Burghers</hi> drawn up in Arms, ranged in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to receive them. The People every where expreſſing the higheſt Satisfaction imaginable, in their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eneral Acclamations and Shouts of Joy; and upon the paſſage of the Bridge, they were met by Twenty Four <hi>Virgins,</hi> Singing Songs of Joy ſuitable to the occaſion; who go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the <hi>Cavelcade,</hi> ſtrowed the way with Fragrant <hi>Herbs</hi> &amp; <hi>Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> &amp; on their Approaching to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154343:20"/>
               <hi>Town-Houſe,</hi> they found a Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal <hi>Arch</hi> fixed very Magnificent, with <hi>Land-Skips,</hi> and <hi>Sylvian Sceens,</hi> with Two Hands on the Top, Claſping each other, <hi>Hierogliphically</hi> ſignifying <hi>Amity:</hi> And over the <hi>Market-Place,</hi> in the High-Street, another <hi>Arch</hi> was Erected, with Devices, and a <hi>Motto</hi> ſuitable to that occaſion. During this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, the <hi>Burghers</hi> made divers Volly's of Shot, and the Loud Thunderings of the <hi>Cannon</hi> ſpread their Approach yet wider, the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs</hi> being very Great and Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</p>
            <p>THERE were likewiſe divers Curious <hi>Fire-Works,</hi> imitating <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> and <hi>Trees</hi> of <hi>Fire, Golden-Hair, Stars</hi> and <hi>Ciphers of Flame.</hi> At Night the Streets were Illuminated, and <hi>Bonefires Blazed</hi> in all the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Towns of the Provinces, and the Entertainments were very Splendid and Magnificent. The <hi>French</hi> continuing their unjuſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154343:20"/>King <hi>Charles</hi> upon this Alliance? diſpatch'd his <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> Impowring the Lord <hi>Hyde,</hi> his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador at the <hi>Hague,</hi> to make and confirm a ſtrict Alliance with the <hi>States General,</hi> mutualy to aſſiſt, ſtand by and defend each other, till they ſhould oblige the <hi>French</hi> King to reaſon, by putting a ſtop and bounds to his Ambitious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; and the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> at that time, declar'd very earneſt in the buſineſs; offering to raiſe divers great Sums of Money, for promoting this affair, &amp; for the recovering Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for injurys done, by ſuch means as ſhould be thought moſt expedient and agreenble; ſo that the King ſent the Lord <hi>Montague</hi> his Ambaſſador to <hi>France,</hi> to preſs for a ſpeedy Reſtitution of ſuch places as were taken, and Detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from his <hi>Confederates</hi> and <hi>Allies,</hi> and upon the triflings and delays of that Court, to come to any reſult as to the Satisfaction demanded:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154343:21"/>An Army was raiſed, and the King of <hi>England</hi> recalled his Forces, that were in the <hi>French</hi> Service, who were partly ſent home, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any payment of their Arrears, which was very conſiderable: And ſo early an effect had this Happy Marriage, in the Alliance it made with <hi>England,</hi> and that the <hi>French</hi> King was in a great Meaſure put to a ſtand, how to proceed: The Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> being ſent over with about 3000 <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Horſe and Foot; and the <hi>Prince</hi> by theſe and other Auxillary Troops, did give a great Defeat to the Duke of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> who Commanded the <hi>French</hi> Army, near <hi>Mons</hi> in <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nault;</hi> had thereupon News, that Purſuant to a former Treaty ſet on foot, a <hi>Peace</hi> was concluded, between the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> and the Crown of <hi>France;</hi> upon the latter deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeveral Towns, that he had, with great Expence of <hi>Blood</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154343:21"/>
               <hi>Treaſure,</hi> taken from the Former: So the War by this means being at an end on this ſide, he returned to the <hi>Hague,</hi> where he was received by the People with the uſual Joy, but from his Illuſtrious <hi>Princeſs</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible; ſeeing his pretious Life had been protected by Providence, in ſo Eminent a Danger, as his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Perſon was expos'd unto: For in the Fight, a <hi>French</hi> Captain being in full Career to Charge him at a diſadvantage, <hi>Monſieur Overkirk,</hi> in a happy moment, Shot that Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who was reaching at the moſt Pretious Life in the World; for which good ſervice, as a grateful acknowledgment, the <hi>States</hi> preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with a <hi>Sword,</hi> whoſe <hi>Hilt</hi> was <hi>Maſſy Gold;</hi> a <hi>Golden</hi> Pair of <hi>Horſe-Buckles,</hi> and a Pair of <hi>Piſtols,</hi> Inlayed with <hi>Gold.</hi> And thus we ſee, this Happy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> in a great meaſure, brought very early, an unexpected <hi>Peace</hi> to the <hi>Waring</hi> Nations.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:154343:22"/>
            <p>THE <hi>French</hi> King having made a <hi>Peace</hi> with the <hi>States General,</hi> it was not long after the reſt of the <hi>Confederates</hi> accorded the like: So that the <hi>Prince</hi> retired from the toils of War, had now again the <hi>Pinceſs</hi>'s Company and Conveſation, which was ſo Winning and Attractive, that nothing but mighty affairs, where Fame and Glory call'd him forth, to ſtop the impetuous Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and ſupport a Tottering State, could have made ſo long a Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or Diſtance.</p>
            <p>AS for the Joy the Court con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at this happy Return of a <hi>Prince,</hi> whoſe preſence (like the <hi>Sun,</hi> coming on this ſide the <hi>Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial,</hi> to revive the Earth with Vernal Rays of kindly heat, after it had been Bound in Icey Chains by the Winters Tyranny) made them forget their former apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Danger, and rendred them Airy and Lively, in hopes of many Happy Days under ſuch a Benign
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154343:22"/>Influence) it is beyound our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and ſo we leave it to the imagination of the Reader.</p>
            <p>BUT this <hi>Peace</hi> to the Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, under Juriſdiction of the <hi>French</hi> King, was not ſo Grateful, for that Reſtleſs Monarch <hi>too</hi> Prone to violence having a Ceſſation of <hi>Arms</hi> abroad, turned wonted Cruelty upon his own Subjects of the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, though upon his Acceſſion to the Throne, they had been the greateſt ſticklers for him, and the chiefeſt means that placed him there, but their Loyalty, nor Proteſtations of a continued Fidelity, availed lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, when it was reſolved their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and Effects ſhould flow into his Coffers.</p>
            <p>UNDER pretence of having but one Religion in his Kindom, he ſent his Dragoons and Bald-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Prieſts</hi> into all the Provinces, to Convert them with <hi>Plunder, Fire, Sword, Racks,</hi> and many New in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Tortures; the Sufferings of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154343:23"/>thoſe Poor people, being more then ſpace will allow to be enumerated in this Hiſtory; eſpecially being ſomewhat forreign to the intended ſubject matter. Let it ſuffice then that their Sufferings moved all the <hi>Princes</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> to pitty, but their own, who ought to have had the greateſt concern for them. The <hi>Pope,</hi> and we believe we might have ſaid, the <hi>Turk,</hi> deteſted this <hi>Cruelty,</hi> that Ruined near 100000 Families, under the Specious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Religion.</p>
            <p>MANY of theſe diſtreſſed peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, fled to <hi>England,</hi> others to <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c.</hi> where they gave Her Highneſs, a new opportunity of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing of her Virtuous inclination, to the performance of Charitable Deeds, ſo naturally inherent to her goodneſs in diſpoſition, and tender Compaſſion to the Diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: So that by her Liberal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, others Were incited and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up, in the Bowels of Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154343:23"/>to relieve thoſe Fugative People; who had left their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, Eſtates, and ſubſtance, for the ſake of a good Conſcience; for would they have turned their Backs upon that Religion they had received, and Embraced the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Idolatry, and Superſtitions, they had been permitted to live in ſome quiet at home; but with what part of their Goods or Eſtate thoſe that were compelled to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatize,</hi> can by their ſevere treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or kind, beſt Teſtify.</p>
            <p>AND becauſe, as may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, their Highneſſes <hi>Charity</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in a great meaſure to the Relief and Shelter, of theſe poor <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> So much <hi>Monſieur</hi> was inraged, that contrary to the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Nimeg uen,</hi> he in full Peace, and the height of Security, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Monſieur <hi>Moran,</hi> Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant of <hi>Provence,</hi> to March 2000 Men into His Highneſſes Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality of <hi>Orange;</hi> which was done
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154343:24"/>under the Command of his Liev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenan General, of <hi>Languedock;</hi> where he threw down the Walls of that City; Plunder'd the Inhabitants, and uſed divers Crueltys, to make many of them turn <hi>Roman-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks;</hi> but in that they could little prevail, yet for all the juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, made by the <hi>States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> upon the occaſion of this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olation of the Treaty; at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of his Highneſs to them, of the wrong he and his Subjects had ſuſtained. No ſatisfactory anſwer could be obtained, but the <hi>French</hi> King unjuſtly and ungenerouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains it till a Juſter Sword ſhall Reeve it from, and put it again in the Hands of the Rightful Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor.</p>
            <p>AND thus we ſee the different tempers of <hi>Princes,</hi> the one La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to Succour and Relieve the Subjects of his Enemy, flying to him for Refuge and Protection; whilſt the other is only pleaſed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154343:24"/>with violence and oppreſſion, and labouring to deſtroy his and his own Subjects. Let theſe Nations conſider then, in what a Fair Line their <hi>Lot</hi> is fallen under, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious Influence of ſo Mild and Gracious a <hi>Prince.</hi> When the Poor Diſtreſſed Subjects of <hi>France</hi> Groan beneath the weight of his Burden, whoſe <hi>Will</hi> is his <hi>Law,</hi> whilſt their <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, in a manner, upon his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>WHILST things were carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on in this manner, the <hi>Princeſs</hi> had cauſe of Sorrow, in the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing News ſhe received of the Death of her Uncle, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, who after Five or Six Days Indiſpoſition, of a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous <hi>Appoplexie,</hi> Dyed at <hi>Whitehall, February</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> 1684. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſetting of this Great and Prudent <hi>Monarch,</hi> gave her Father Acceſſion to the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Throne, yet his Love and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:154343:25"/>Care of Her Welfare, and Proſperity, all along had made ſo deep an impreſſion in her <hi>Princely</hi> Heart, that it Melted her Eyes in <hi>Pearls</hi> of unfeigned Sorrow, and threw a Cloud of <hi>Sadneſs</hi> over the Livelyneſs of her Active Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, nor was her Royal Conſort, wanting, as in her Joys, ſo to ſhare with her in her Grief; for never any Royal Pair, were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to Simpathize ſo nearly with each other, in the paſſions of the Mind; as theſe Illuſtrious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which ſhowed the <hi>Quintiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cential</hi> perfection of Love in its Brighteſt Mortal Refinement.</p>
            <p>UPON this <hi>Sadneſs,</hi> as well that <hi>Court,</hi> as the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> went into the Deepeſt <hi>Mourning;</hi> and on the <hi>14th</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> the <hi>Royal Corps</hi> in a Private <hi>Funeral,</hi> was <hi>Buried</hi> in King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>7ths Chappel,</hi> in a <hi>Vault,</hi> under the <hi>Eaſt End</hi> of the <hi>South-Iſle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>Prince</hi> to divert his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154343:25"/>on this ſad occaſion, went to viſit ſeveral Towns, to take a view how they ſtood in Repair, as to their Fortifications, as alſo to ſettle the <hi>Military</hi> affairs; and upon Returning from <hi>Hounſlyr-dyke</hi> to the <hi>Hague;</hi> gave Audience to divers Forreign Miniſters, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving viſited ſome other Towns, he was Met at <hi>Loo</hi> by her Highneſs, where there were ſplendid Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments and Rejoycings; and King <hi>James,</hi> after the Death of King <hi>Charles,</hi> having been Proclaim'd, and on the <hi>23d</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1685, Crown'd at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Sent the Marqueſs <hi>D' Alberville,</hi> his Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador to <hi>Holland;</hi> who in <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> had Audience of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> whereupon they Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed, till the Seventh of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN the mean while, on the firſt of that <hi>Month,</hi> the <hi>Princeſs</hi> with preparations of Curious <hi>Fire-Works,</hi> Repreſenting a Battel, Ranged in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154343:26"/>Four Lines, and Furniſhed out with ſeveral <hi>Batterys,</hi> in a very Lively manner, expreſſing the Actions of a Fight.</p>
            <p>AND now, King <hi>James</hi> having Declar'd himſelf a <hi>Roman Catholick;</hi> and upon the Defeat and Cutting off the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Argyle</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and gotten him a <hi>Standing Army</hi> (though the <hi>Parliament</hi> deſign'd it ſhould be <hi>Disbanded</hi>) things began to run high, and <hi>Rome</hi> drave on <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hue</hi> like, to gain her End. And, after a time, other practices failing, ſhe began openly to puſh at the <hi>Church of England.</hi> Swarms of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and others of the <hi>Romiſh Order,</hi> daily flocking into this <hi>Kingdom</hi> like Swarms of <hi>Locuſts:</hi> And attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with the ſame boldneſs, in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and eſpecially about the <hi>Princes Court,</hi> notwithſtanding the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion that had been made on their behalf, by ſome <hi>Mineſters</hi> Reſiding there, the <hi>Court of Juſtice</hi> at the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154343:26"/>
               <hi>Hague,</hi> by a <hi>Decree,</hi> Commanded them to Retire out of that Country, not any more to Return, Being Unhing'd there, they, for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part, return'd to <hi>England:</hi> Where they were welcome to the <hi>Court,</hi> but not to the generality of the People. Who ſeeing Affairs <hi>Sicken,</hi> and the <hi>Diſtemper</hi> they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in <hi>Government,</hi> began to wiſh for a <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> to apply <hi>Healing Medicines</hi> to the <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> e're it grew Dangerous, and beyond all <hi>Cure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND among other Siniſter Practices, Managed and Suggeſted by <hi>Evil Counſellors</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who bore the greateſt ſway in the <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> they lay'd hold on the <hi>Pillars of the Eſtabliſhed Church;</hi> and at one bold puſh, thruſt Seven of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> into <hi>Priſon;</hi> and ſoon after <hi>Baited</hi> them, at a <hi>Tryal,</hi> with (in a manner) <hi>Bear-garden</hi> treatment, only for <hi>Petitioning</hi> that they might not be forced to do what was contrary to their <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Conſciences.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:154343:27"/>
            <p>THEN the Startled Nation; (oppreſſed with many grievous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurys) perceiving all that was Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and Dear to it, going to be ſwallow'd in an <hi>Abiſs</hi> of <hi>Popery;</hi> and the many Miſerys that uſually attend a Change of <hi>Government,</hi> (and the Aboliſhing of the <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws</hi>) began to ſtretch out her hand in earneſt, for help and ſuccour. And having caſt her Eyes round about, at laſt ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fixed them, upon an Illuſtrious <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>Princeſs,</hi> always com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate to the Diſtreſſed; and to whom ſucceding Generations are bound, for the ſo <hi>Wonderful a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance,</hi> wrought in our Days.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Court</hi> party here in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> had been Tampering, but in vain, to bring their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> to ſome agreeableneſs with their proceedings, as is evident by the Anſwer, <hi>Minheer Fagel,</hi> (that great <hi>Stateſ-man,</hi> Pentionary of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Frieze-Land</hi>) Returned
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:154343:27"/>to Mr. <hi>Stewart,</hi> who wrote to him, to have their Highneſſes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, or rather Approbation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſt,</hi> which was not done upon his own head as a Private Perſon, but by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. The which take Briefly, thus.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>THAT their Highneſſes have often Declared, as they more particularly did to the Marqueſs</hi> D' Albeville <hi>Ambaſſador Extraordinary from</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, <hi>to the</hi> States General: <hi>That it is their Opinion, that no Chriſtian ought to be Perſecuted for his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or Opinion in Religion; or be the worſe uſed becauſe he differs from the Publick Eſtabliſhed Church, and Religion; and therefore they could be content, that even the</hi> Papiſts <hi>might be ſuſſered to continue in their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, with as much Liberty as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them by the</hi> States of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Provinces: <hi>And as for the</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters, <hi>their</hi> Highneſſes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:154343:28"/>
                  <hi>did not only Conſent, but Heartily Approve of their Entire Priviledge, for the Full and Free Exerciſe of their Liberty, without any Trouble or Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That their</hi> Highneſſes, <hi>in caſe the</hi> King <hi>deſired it, were willing to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their willingneſs to concur in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Confirming and Setling this Liberty as far as lay in them; and were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, upon the like deſire, to concur in repealing the Laws, always provide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thoſe Laws remain ſtill in Force, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> full Vigour, whereby</hi> Roman-Catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licks <hi>are Excluded both</hi> Houſes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Parliament, <hi>out of all Employment Eccleſlaſtical, Civil, and Military<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and alſo all thoſe other Laws, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> confirm the Proteſtant Religion, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſecure it againſt the Attempts of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But that their</hi> Highneſſes <hi>could n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> by any means agree to the Repealin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Teſts or thoſe Penal Laws th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> tend to the Securitie of the</hi> Proteſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:154343:28"/>
                  <hi>Religion, ſince the</hi> Roman-Catholicks <hi>received no more Prejudice from thoſe then that being Excluded from Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or from Publick Employments; and by them the</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Religion is ſheltered, and Cover'd from all the Deſigns of the</hi> Roman-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks <hi>againſt it, or againſt the Publick ſafety; and that neither the</hi> Teſt <hi>nor thoſe</hi> Laws <hi>can be ſaid to carry in them any Severity, upon the account of Conſcience, they being only Pernicious Qualifing perſons to be Members of Parliament, or of bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Offices, by which they muſt declare themſelves, before God and Man, to be Proteſtants: So that all this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to no more, than ſecuring the Proteſtant Religion from any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice it may receive from</hi> Roman-Catholicks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That their</hi> Higneſſes <hi>have thought, and ſtill are of the Opinion, that more than this ought not to be required, or expected from them, ſince by this means of the</hi> Roman Catholicks, <hi>and their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154343:29"/>Poſterity, would be always ſecured from every Manner of Trouble in their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Eſtates, or in the Fxerciſe of their Religion; and that they ought to be ſatisfied with this, and not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet the Kingdom becauſe they are not admitted to ſit in Parliament, or bear publick Offices; or becauſe thoſe Laws, in which the Security of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion doth chiefly conſiſt, are not Repealed, by which they may be put in a Condition to Overturn it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>THAT their Highneſſes believed likewiſe, that the Diſſenters would be for ever ſatisfied, when they ſhould be for ever Cover'd, from all Danger of being diſturbed, or Puniſhed for the free Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Religion, upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or condition of their Religion, whatſoever,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>BY this means the good Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and ſecure the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> being known to the Adverſe Party, they began to take other
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:154343:29"/>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; and poſted ſo faſt in their courſe, to puſh on our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerys, that they not only Run their Policys out of Breath, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at laſt out of the Kingdom; for the chief <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> ſeeing all at Stake, that the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty affairs were managed by <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> or ſuch as for intereſt or prejudice were no Friends to the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>They Addreſſed themſelves to their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> to ſave a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, in which they might juſtly Claim ſo great an Intereſt.</p>
            <p>TO this they gave an Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ear, ſaw us at the Brink of Ruine, and came (as ſent by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,) in a happy time, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent our Falling into it: For when thoſe that were labouring to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturn our Religion, Laws, and Chain (at leaſt) our Liberties much ſhorter; thought themſelves ſure of Gaining the Point; and that though their weak rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:154343:30"/>could not work any thing upon the Generality of the people, yet relying on that confidence, that moſtly failed them, <hi>Viz.</hi> That they were Backed, and would be ſupported by a very conſiderable <hi>Army,</hi> which had been kept up in Summer Campaigns, ſeveral Years, at <hi>Hounſlow-Heath,</hi> and in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Quarters ſo Poſted, that they might the better Awe the Nation: They found themſelves on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Deceived, and ſo over whel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with fears, that the Chain of all the meaſures they had long been Linking, with much Labour and Coſt, inſtantly ſnapt in ſunder.</p>
            <p>UPON News that the <hi>Prince</hi> was preparing to be our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, all that had been done by the <hi>Court</hi> party, was untwiſted, <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> were Surrendred, Juſtices, and other Magiſtrates and Officers that had been outed to make room for <hi>Roman-Catholicks,</hi> reſtored, as alſo was <hi>Magdalen Colledge,</hi> and the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:154343:30"/>Biſhop of <hi>Londons</hi> Suſpenſion ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off: The Seven Biſhops, that had been Impriſoned and Tryed, were ſent for to <hi>Court,</hi> and not only received into Favour, but Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed and Adviſed withal. Father <hi>Peter,</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> diſmiſt the <hi>Council,</hi> and the King declar'd, he was willing that <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> ſhould remain uncapable to be Members of the <hi>Houſe of Commons.</hi> Oh the wonderful Converſions of Fear! what the Prayers and Intreaties of the <hi>Nobles, Biſhops,</hi> and the deſires of all the good <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> could not do, the very name of their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> preparation, brought to paſs. But not to Dwell too long on this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Prince,</hi> whoſe actions are ſwift in <hi>Execution</hi> as his purpoſes, delayed not, though it was in the dead of <hi>Winter,</hi> and his <hi>Fleet</hi> was put back in the <hi>Harbour,</hi> by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Winds, and ſuffer'd ſome
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:154343:31"/>little damage, reſolved on this great Work, on the <hi>Fifth of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> (a day whereon another great deliverance happened to this Nation, and tho' long ſince, yet freſh in our minds) He came with his whole <hi>Fleet</hi> before <hi>Torbay,</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> not having met wih any Oppoſition from the <hi>Engliſh Fleet,</hi> though he paſſed by within <hi>Cannon</hi> Shot, inſomuch that this gave a happy Preſage that God had Bowd the Hearts of the People to be at their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion; and what more confirmed it was, when the firſt Men were put on Shoar, <hi>Viz.</hi> about 500, to put themſelves in a Poſture for the better ſecuring the Landing of the reſt, ſo far were the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey people from Flying their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, or any Conſternation, that on the contrary, they came Flock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Welcome them on Shoar, bringing them a ſupply of ſuch Proviſions as they had; and when
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:154343:31"/>the <hi>Prince</hi> Landed ſuch were the Shouts and Applaudities, that theſe <hi>Weſtern</hi> Countreys never Rung with the like Melody.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Fleet</hi> conſiſting of 635 Men of War, Flyboats, Pinks and Fireſhips; and the Forces that Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 14352, a great many of them being <hi>Brandenburgers, Heſs Caſſelers, Sweeds &amp;c.</hi> And with them divers great Commanders, with ſome <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Noblemen, and a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others.</p>
            <p>AND now the Nations <hi>Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> bends low, to Welcome and to Complement a <hi>Heroe</hi> who brought her Safety with him; for as well the <hi>Nobles,</hi> as others, came Crouding in, and only a <hi>March</hi> was made, and not a <hi>War,</hi> for thoſe who had boaſted ſuch mighty things before, Fled and Scatter'd at the <hi>Martial</hi> Noiſe of his <hi>Drums</hi> and <hi>Trumpets;</hi> that very <hi>Army</hi> on which they had ſo much Rely'd, coming in a great meaſure over to him;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:154343:32"/>and to be brief, he with little o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no Effuſion of Blood, King (<hi>Jame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> being retir'd) took a quiet poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Kingdom, amidſt the Loud Shouts and Acclamations o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the People, being every where Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed, and Congratulated.</p>
            <p>THIS News Flying into <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> cauſed not only Exceſs of Joy in the <hi>Princeſs,</hi> for the Safety o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her Illuſtrious <hi>Conſort,</hi> whoſe grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> undertaking, had Subjected He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Spirits to Doubts and Fears, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Hazards that might attend ſuch an Enterprize; but with her tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whole Nation Simpathiz'd, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the high Satisfaction the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conceived upon his Succeſs and Proſperous Fortune: And whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he had here, at the earneſt requeſt of the <hi>States</hi> Aſſembled in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, taken the Adminiſtration of the Publick affairs of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into his Hands, and after King <hi>James</hi>'s leaving the Kingdom, and going to <hi>France,</hi> the Citizens of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:154343:32"/>
               <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> went in a great Body to the <hi>Parliament-houſe</hi> where they delivered two Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Subſtance of them being to this Effect. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>THAT they moſt Humbly and Earneſtly Deſired, that His Moſt Illuſtrious Highneſs, the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> might be ſpeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ily ſetled in the <hi>Throne,</hi> by whoſe Conduct, Courage, and Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the <hi>Nation</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> might be Secured and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, from it's Enemys at home and abroad. That <hi>Ireland</hi> (which was then in Rebellion) might be reſcued from its deplorable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; and to conclude, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſetled on a laſting Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and Security, in Peace, and Liberty.</q>
            </p>
            <p>UPON this, Her Highneſs ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been Complemented at the <hi>Hague,</hi> by all the Perſons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that on purpoſe Reſorted to the Court, and among others their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:154343:33"/>
               <hi>Electorl Highneſſes</hi> of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> &amp; She having made to the Latter a very Splendid Entertainment; it was concluded here, that the Illuſtrious <hi>Princeſs</hi> ſhould be ſent for over, to be Partner in thoſe Crowns the Wiſdom of the Nation had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to lay at the <hi>Pinceſs</hi>'s Feet, to which ſhe conſenting: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on her Departure for <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> the <hi>States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> the <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> the <hi>Council of State,</hi> and the <hi>Colledges,</hi> either in Bodys or by their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putys, attended her, and made their Complements and Congratulations on the happy occaſion; and in this the Forreign Miniſters reſiding at <hi>Court,</hi> had a ſhare, and the Perſons of Quality of both Sexes. The <hi>Majeſtrates</hi> made it their Requeſt, that the <hi>Burghers</hi> might wait on her in <hi>Arms,</hi> but ſhe modeſtly refuſed it, as being too tedious a Cerimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for the intended Expeditneſs: however, the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:154343:33"/>Deputed Three of their Body to Wait upon her, till ſhe ſhould be Embarqued, and gave Orders to the <hi>Sieur Allemond,</hi> with Divers <hi>Men of War,</hi> to Joyn Admiral <hi>Herbert,</hi> who attended with a Squadron and ſeveral Yatches, to Tranſport her for <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE people at her Departure, ſcarce refraining expreſſing their Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows in Tears, that ſo much Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Goodneſs had left their Shoar, to inrich another Land. They had ſeen her worth, and valued it at ſuch a Rate, that though ſhe went as it were in Triumph, to poſſeſs Crowns and Kingdoms, they Grudged to be Deprived of ſuch a Bleſſing, or ſpare it to any other: Like the People of <hi>Mittelene,</hi> when <hi>Cornelia</hi> the Wife of <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, was to go with her Lord after the <hi>Pharſalian War,</hi> left their Shoars, tho' in a different State and Circumſtance; they all crouded on the <hi>Rocks,</hi> and <hi>Sands,</hi> and fixed their
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:154343:34"/>eager eyes on the Ship She was in, till the diſtance of ſpace had removed it from their ſight. For ſetting ſail with a Proſperous Wind, She ſoon reached the ſhoars She was diſtined by Providence to Crown with bleſſings, where Her Welcome was Proclaimed by the Guns from the Ships in the Road, and from the Forts, and after them, by the Ringing of Bells, and the Joyful Acclamations of the People; and as She came up the River, the Tower, on which the Royal Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was Diſplay'd, made <hi>London</hi> Senſible in a Language of Fire, breathed from its Thundering Cannons, that its Beloved Darling approached to Croud upon it great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er advantages than it had long time participated.</p>
            <p>ON the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>February</hi> in the Evening, the <hi>Princeſs</hi> Arived at <hi>White-hall,</hi> where ſhe was received according to her Royal Character, by the Nobles and great Ladys of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:154343:34"/>the <hi>Court;</hi> and by the <hi>Prince</hi> with all the Tender endearments and Expreſſions of kindneſs and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The ſame Night ſhe received the Complements of the Nobility at <hi>Court,</hi> whilſt the Streets every where Shined with <hi>Bonfires,</hi> and Illuminations, and the <hi>Bells</hi> charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Air into a ſtilneſs, by the <hi>Harmony of their deſired Muſick;</hi> and, to be Brief, a general Joy ſpread it ſelf through the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, for her preſence, of which ſo long an abſence had deprived it.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Arival of the Princeſs, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had the conſent of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and his Royal <hi>Conſort,</hi> to accept of the <hi>Kingly Dignity,</hi> delayed not in their Reſolves to have them Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi> of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland: Scotland</hi> being an <hi>Independant Kingdom,</hi> and not within the Juriſdiction of a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Whoſe <hi>Crown</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:154343:35"/>however, was ſoon after Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>States,</hi> in like manner; of the Proceedings, in which we ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>THE Reſolves in Order to the Proclaiming, being on theſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, <hi>That</hi> WILLIAM <hi>and</hi> MARY, <hi>Prince and Princeſs of</hi> Orange, <hi>be Declared</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Queen, <hi>of</hi> England, France, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>with all the Dominions and Dependencys, thereunto belonging, to hold the</hi> Crown <hi>and</hi> Royal Dignity <hi>of thoſe Kingdoms and Dominions during their Lives, and the Life of the Surviver of them; and that the Sole and Full Exerciſe of the</hi> Kingly <hi>Power be only in, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted by his</hi> Highneſs, <hi>in the Name of Himſelf and the Princeſs, for the Term of their Lives, and after their Deceaſe, the</hi> Crown <hi>and</hi> Dignitys Royal <hi>of the Kingdoms and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, to be left to the Heirs of the Body of the</hi> Princeſs, <hi>and for default of ſuch Iſſue, to the Princeſs</hi> Ann
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:154343:35"/>
               <hi>of</hi> Denmark, <hi>and the Heirs of her Body, and for default of ſuch Iſſue, to the Heirs of the Body of the</hi> Prince.</p>
            <p>AND then an Oath of <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> was Enacted, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>Do ſincerely Promiſe and Swear, that I will be Faithful and bear True</hi> Allegiance <hi>to Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtys, King</hi> WILLIAM <hi>and Queen</hi> MARY.</p>
               <p>So Help me GOD.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do Sincerely Promiſe and Swear, that I do from my Heart ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor, Deteſt, and Abjure, as</hi> Impious <hi>&amp;</hi> Heretical, <hi>the Damnable Doctrine, and Poſition, that</hi> Princes <hi>Excomu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, or Deprived by the Pope, or any Authority of the</hi> See <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>may be Depoſed or Murthered by their Subjects, or any other whatſoever. And I do Declare, that no Forreign Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State, or Potentate, hath, or ought to have any Juriſdiction, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:154343:36"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:154343:36"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:154343:37"/>Superiority, Preheminence, or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>this Realm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So Help me GOD.</p>
            </q>
            <p>THIS and other Proceedings, preceding the Happy Proclaiming, the Wiſh of the Nation Enſued; for the <hi>Officers at Arms, Sergeants at Arms, Trumpets,</hi> and others, whoſe Office it was to attend in this Important Occaſion, being in a Readineſs, by the Order His Grace the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Norfolk, Earl Marſhal</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> at <hi>White-hall-gate,</hi> and Sir <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas St. George, Garter Principal King at Arms,</hi> receiving a Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was Ordered by the Lords forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to Proclaim it: And <hi>York He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauld,</hi> after the Third Sounding of the <hi>Trumpets,</hi> Proclaim'd it: <hi>Garter King at Arms,</hi> Reading it by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods, whilſt he repeated in the preſence of the Lords and Commons and a vaſt number of Gentry, and others, who by their Acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:154343:37"/>of Joy, expreſſed their high ſatisfaction in what was done; and ſo, in Excellent Order, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded through <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Two <hi>Temple-Gates,</hi> made the Like Proclamation, and twice more Repeated it, <hi>Viz.</hi> At <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet-End</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide;</hi> and before the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> in <hi>Cornhill;</hi> being in all theſe places concluded with Joyful Shouts and Acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and ſoon after they were, with the ſame deſire of a willing people, Proclaimed in the Cities, and chief <hi>Borroughs</hi> and <hi>Towns</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and in the Dominion of <hi>Wales, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND now our <hi>Epethite,</hi> by their advancement to the <hi>Royal Dignity,</hi> muſt be changed. The King on the <hi>25th</hi> of <hi>February</hi> for himſelf, and on the behalf of the Queen, was pleaſed to expreſs to both <hi>Houſes,</hi> in Anſwer to their Declaration, his high Satisfaction in what they had done, and graciouſly Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:154343:38"/>them the Utmoſt of his Care and Protection, for the Security and Preſervation of their <hi>Laws, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> and was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly willing to <hi>Concur</hi> with them in any thing that might be for the Good and Advancement of the Kingdom, and to do all that in him lay, to promote the Glory and Welfare of the Nation. And ſoon after the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> went with the Body of the <hi>Clergy</hi> of that City, to pay their Majeſties an Humble Tender of their Duty and Fidelity, Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the great Satisfaction they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived upon Their Majeſties Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Throne; and being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Kiſs the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> Hands, His Majeſty at the ſame time giving them a Satisfactory Aſſurance of his Extraordinary Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and of his utmoſt protection and encouragement to them, concluding <hi>I aſſure you, you ſhall find it ſo, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:154343:38"/>may depend upon it.</hi> And in this indeed, (as it is promiſed in <hi>Holy Writ</hi>) we have found in the care and protection of a <hi>King &amp; Queen,</hi> the truly <hi>Nurſing Father,</hi> and <hi>Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Mother</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>Convention</hi> having reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it ſelf unto a <hi>Free Parliament,</hi> an <hi>Act</hi> was Paſſed, Entituled, <hi>An Act for removing and preventing all Queſtions and Diſputes about the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling and ſitting of the preſent Parliament;</hi> and preparations were making for the Relieſ of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> whom the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts,</hi> countenanced by the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> who had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for the Late <hi>King James,</hi> Miſerably <hi>Murthered, Plundered, &amp; Haraſſed,</hi> in moſt parts of that <hi>Kingdom.</hi> But <hi>Scotland</hi> had got the upper hand of thoſe that ſtood out for the <hi>Abdicated King;</hi> And it their <hi>Convention,</hi> upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of a <hi>Letter</hi> from his <hi>Majeſty</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> they, after a few De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:154343:39"/>
               <hi>Declar'd</hi> the <hi>Throne Vacant,</hi> and ſoon after concluded to lay their <hi>Crown,</hi> as <hi>England</hi> had done, at thee Feet of King WILLIAM, and Queen MARY: That they ſhould be Crowned <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the <hi>Crown,</hi> with an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> to Rugulate and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle particulars, Offered them.</p>
            <p>WHILST the <hi>Genious</hi> of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Bowed thus Low to the beſt of <hi>Princes, a Proclamation</hi> was <hi>Iſſued</hi> out here by the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi> to Inform the <hi>Peers,</hi> and ſuch as claimed by Tenure or Offices, that the <hi>Solemnitie</hi> of the <hi>Coronation,</hi> was to be performed on the <hi>Eleventh</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1689, and accordingly <hi>Magnificent</hi> preparations were made againſt that happy day, and on the <hi>Ninth</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> in order to it, An <hi>Act</hi> Paſſed, Entituled, <hi>An Act for Eſtabliſhing the Coronation Oath.</hi> The form of it being in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner following <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>THE <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Biſhop</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <stage>ſhall
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:154343:39"/>ſay,</stage>
                  <p>Will you Solemnly Promiſe and Swear, to Govern the People of this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and the Domin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions thereto belonging, according to the Statutes in Parliament agree'd on, and the Laws and Cuſtoms of the ſame?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <stage>ſhall ſay,</stage>
                  <p>I Solemnly Promiſe ſo to do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Biſhop,</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Will you, to your Power, cauſe Law and Juſtice, in Mercy, to be Executed in all your Judgments?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Biſhop,</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Will you, to the utmoſt of your Power, Maintain the Law of God, the True Profeſſion of the Goſpel, and the Proteſtant Reform'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion Eſtabliſhed by Law: and will you preſerve unto the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> of this Realm, and unto Churches Committed to their Charge, all ſuch Rights and Priviledges as by Law do or ſhall appertain to any of them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>All this I Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to do.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>After this the King and Queen,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:154343:40"/>laying their Hands on the <hi>Holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> ſhall ſay,</p>
               <sp>
                  <p>Theſe things, which I have here before Promiſed, I will Perform and Keep. <hi>So help me GOD.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </q>
            <p>AND by Virtue of the ſame <hi>Act</hi> this <hi>Oath</hi> is to be Adminiſtred to the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens,</hi> that ſhall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſucceed to the Crown.</p>
            <p>THE Nations <hi>Jubilie</hi> (as we may term it) being now come: The <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> came from <hi>White-Hall</hi> to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> whilſt the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raulds</hi> and other <hi>Officers at Arms</hi> were ordering the Procedings, after a litle ſtay, about <hi>Eleven</hi> in the Morning the whole Proceeding paſſed into the Great Hall, from the <hi>Lords Houſe</hi> and <hi>Painted Chamber,</hi> at the upper end whereof a <hi>Throne,</hi> was <hi>Erected,</hi> and on it Their <hi>Majeſties</hi> took Their Seats under a <hi>Canopy</hi> of State, whilſt the <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of the <hi>Jewel-Houſe</hi> brought and preſented the Swords to the <hi>Lord High Conſtable, viz.</hi> That of State,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:154343:40"/>that called <hi>Curtana,</hi> and the Two Pointed Swords, in their proper Order, who delivered them in the ſame Order, to the Lord Great Chamberlain, who having Drawn them, Preſented them on the Table, before the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen;</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the <hi>Spurs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>UPON this the <hi>Dean</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendaries</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> brought and Preſented the <hi>Crowns,</hi> and the other <hi>Regalia,</hi> in their proper manner: and theſe again were delivered to thoſe whoſe Claim it was to bear them.</p>
            <p>THINGS being thus fixed, the Proceeding paſſed from <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Hall</hi> to the <hi>Abby,</hi> in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Order; and every one pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in their Station and Degree: Silence being made, the <hi>Recogniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was begun, by the Lord <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>London;</hi> at the end of which there was a General Shout, and Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, of high Satisfaction among the People. The <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> then Offered, and the <hi>Noblemen</hi> that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:154343:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:154343:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:154343:42"/>carry'd the <hi>Regalia,</hi> Offered them ſeverally at the <hi>Altar;</hi> there to be diſpoſed of: Then the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of St. <hi>Aſaph</hi> and <hi>Bangor,</hi> Sung the <hi>Littany;</hi> after which the <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Service</hi> begun. The <hi>Epiſtle</hi> was Read by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Carliſle,</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel</hi> by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of St. <hi>Aſaph:</hi> After this, the <hi>Nicene Creed</hi> was Read, and by this time the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Saliſbury</hi> being in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> Preach'd an Excellent <hi>Sermon</hi> on the Occaſion; from theſe Words, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>THE GOD of</hi> IſrAel <hi>ſaid, The rock of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſpake to Me: He that Ruleth over Men, muſt be Juſt, Ruling in the Fear of GOD: And he ſhall be as the Light of the Morning, when the Sun Riſeth, even a Morning without Clouds, as the Tender Graſs Springeth out of the Earth by Clear Shining af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Rain.</hi> 2 Sam. 23.3, 4.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To which the Pious <hi>Queen,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:154343:42"/>was all the while obſerved to be very Attentive. The Charms of Power and Greatneſs, with all the Splendid Pomp and Cerimony, could not avert her thoughts from the more Serious Contemplation of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things.</p>
            <p>(BUT not to Digreſs in the midſt of this Cerimony) The Sermon ended, Their Majeſties took the beforementioned Oath, and <hi>Voni Creator</hi> being Sung, and the Anointing <hi>Oyl</hi> Conſecrated, Their Majeſties were Conducted to the Chairs placedon a <hi>Theatre,</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robed of their Crimſon Mantles and Solemnly Anointed; then preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Spurs and Sword, which were Offer'd up and Redeemed by the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Portland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>UPON this the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> were Clad, and Inveſted with the Imperial Robes, and the Orbs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to them; and after that the Rings and Scepters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:154343:43"/>about Four in the Afternoon, the Royal Diadems were placed on Their Heads, by the Lord <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Aſſiſted by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rocheſter.</hi> Then the Trumpets Sounded, the Drums Beat; the Thundering of the Great Guns, with the Peoples Shouts Proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the News. The <hi>Peers and Peer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſes</hi> hereupon put on their <hi>Coronets;</hi> and the BIBLE was preſented to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen;</hi> after this they Kiſſed the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and then <hi>Te Deum</hi> was Sung, and thereupon they Aſcended the Throne; The <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> doing their Homage, and Kiſſed Their Majeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Left Cheeks, and then the Temporal Peers did the like; whilſt the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> of the Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold caſt the <hi>Meddals</hi> among the people: and after this, began the <hi>Communion,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> made their ſecond Offering, and Receiving the Holy Sacrament, they Entred in their Robes of State, to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:154343:43"/>St. <hi>Edwards Chappel,</hi> where they were Diveſted of the Imperial <hi>Pall, &amp;c.</hi> And having Robes of <hi>Purple Velvet</hi> put on them, they returned with their <hi>Crowns</hi> on their Heads in the ſame Order they came, the <hi>Peers</hi> and <hi>Peereſſes</hi> now wearing their <hi>Coronets,</hi> and Entring the Great Hall at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> a Royal Entertainment was provided, of all that is Rare and Coſtly, ſeveral Tables being Furniſhed out in the moſt Delicious manner, and <hi>Charles Dymock</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Their Majeſties Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, between the Firſt and Second Courſe, came Riding Compleatly Armed into the Hall, Conducted by the Lord <hi>High Conſtable,</hi> and the Earl <hi>Marſhal,</hi> on Horſe-back likewiſe, and his Challenge pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by <hi>York Herauld, Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>If any Perſon of what Degree ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, High or Low, ſhall Deny or gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay our Soveraign Lord and Lady, King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> King and Queen of <hi>England, France</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:154343:44"/>and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defenders of the Faith, to be Rightful King and Queen of <hi>England,</hi> or that they ought not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Imperial Crown of the ſame, Here is their Champion, who ſaith he Lyeth, and is a Falſe Traytor, being ready in Perſon to Combate with him, and in this Quarrel will Venture his Life againſt him, on what Day ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he ſhall be appointed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>After this Their Majeſties Royal Stiles were Proclaim'd in <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and every thing was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with the Exacteſt Order and Decency, concluding about Eight of the Clock, when Their Majeſties returned to <hi>Whitehall;</hi> and the reſt of the Evening was ſpent in <hi>Bonfires, Ringing of Bells,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Demonſtrations of Joy.</p>
            <p>THIS happy Corronation uſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er'd in the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> being Proclaim'd in <hi>Scotland;</hi> for after the <hi>States</hi> had paſſed the <hi>Vote</hi> to that purpoſe, in the <hi>Convention</hi> of that Kingdom, they Aſſiſted by the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:154343:44"/>
               <hi>Magiſtrates, Lord Provoſt,</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Edinborough,</hi> went to the Market Croſs, where <hi>Lyon King at Arms,</hi> aſſiſted by the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raulds</hi> and <hi>Purſuvants,</hi> Proclaimed them <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Scotland, &amp;c.</hi> The Trumpets Sounding and the Peoples Shoutings expreſſing the Joy conceived on this Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And ſoon after they were Proclaimed in all the Citys and principal <hi>Boroughs</hi> of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>ON the <hi>18th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1689, the Sieur <hi>Shemettan</hi> Extraordinary En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy from the Duke of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> Complement Their Majeſties in his firſt Audience, upon their Acceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Throne. Nor was the <hi>Scots</hi> Nation ſlow in preſenting their Crown. The States Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> Sir <hi>James Montgomery,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Dalrimple</hi> their <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> to that purpoſe. At the ſame time cauſing a Day of <hi>Thankſgiving</hi> to be ſet apart for
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:154343:45"/>their Deliverance from <hi>Popery, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ON the <hi>11th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſioners waited on the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> in the <hi>Banquetting-Houſe</hi> at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and preſented a Letter from the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and after that an Inſtrument of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, then a Writing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining divers grievances, which they Humbly Pray'd might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd; upon the Reading of which, His Majeſty was pleaſed to return this Gracious and Satisfactory An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>WHEN I Engaged in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, I had particular Regard and Conſideration for the Kingdom of</hi> Scotland, <hi>and therefore I did E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a Declaration in Relation to that as well as this Kingdom, which I intend to make Good and Effectual to them. I take it very Kindly, that</hi> Scotland <hi>hath Expreſſed ſo much Confidence in, &amp; Affection to me. They ſhall find the willing to Aſſiſt them
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:154343:45"/>in every thing that concerns the Weal and Intereſt of that Kingdom, for making what Laws ſhall be Neceſſary for the Security of their Religion, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, and Liberty, and to eaſe them, of what may be juſtly grievous to them.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Coronation Oath was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Tendred to Their <hi>Majeſties,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Argyle</hi> as chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner Reading it by periods, and the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> holding up their Hands, as is the manner of <hi>Scotland</hi> in this matter of taking Oaths, repeated it till they came to the Clauſe where the Rooting out of <hi>Hereticks</hi> is mentioned in that Oath, at which his Majeſty declared, <q>That He did not mean by thoſe words, that he was under any Obligation to become a Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor.</q> To which the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners anſwered, <q>That neither the meaning of the <hi>Oath,</hi> neither did the Laws of <hi>Scotland</hi> Import it; and that the <hi>States of Scotland</hi> had Authorized them, to repreſent to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:154343:46"/>Their Majeſties, that that Clauſe did not Import the Deſtroying of <hi>Hereticks;</hi> for by the Laws of <hi>Scotland,</hi> no man was to be perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for his private Opinion; and tht Obſtinate and Convicted <hi>Heriticks</hi> only, were to be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced Rebels, and Outlaw'd; whereby their Moveable Eſtates were to be Confiſcated.</q> Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the <hi>King</hi> Ordering the <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners</hi> to witneſs he took the Oath in that ſenſe. The Words of the whole Tenour of it being repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Their <hi>Majeſties</hi> Sign'd it, and ſo the Commiſſioners departed with Joy and Thankfulneſs: And on the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> enſuing, the <hi>States</hi> met, and being Aſſembled, it was ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd to them, by His Grace the Duke of <hi>Hamilton,</hi> that the King had ſent him a Commiſſion, to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent his Perſon in the enſuing <hi>Parliament,</hi> and that he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved inſtructions to turn the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> into a <hi>Free Parliament:</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:154343:46"/>whereupon they proceeded to paſs an <hi>Act</hi> for that purpoſe, and made it High Treaſon to Queſtion or Diſown the Authority of its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch. Upon which the Duke of <hi>Gowrdon</hi> who had a long time held the Caſtle of <hi>Edinborough,</hi> upon the account of the Intereſt of King <hi>James,</hi> Articling for the ſafety of thoſe that were with him, threw himſelf wholly upon Their Majeſties Mercy, and Clemency, ſaying, <hi>That he had ſo much Reſpect for all the Princes of the Line of King</hi> James <hi>the</hi> 6th, <hi>that he would make no Conditions with them as to his own particular Intereſt, but Render himſelf entirely to their own Diſcretion:</hi> And thereupon delivered up that Strong Place to Sir <hi>John Lanier,</hi> Deputed to receive it at his hands, and although the Viſcount <hi>Dundee</hi> made Head for a time, yet upon the Entry of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces under the Command of Major General <hi>Mack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ay,</hi> he was Killed in a Battel near
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:154343:47"/>the <hi>Blare</hi> of <hi>Athol;</hi> and ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the whole Kingdom of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was Reduced to Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Obedience,</p>
            <p>THUS Heaven as it proſper'd their other affairs, ſo in this gave Succeſs to their Arms, and brought fear where Love and Obedience was deny'd, under whoſe Auſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fortune the Proteſtants of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> having ſhaken off their firſt fears, took Courage, Fortifying <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don-Derry</hi> and other places, and making a very conſiderable head, not without great ſucceſs in the Field, till ſuch Reliefs and Succours were brought them as Reduced that Kingdom to its Obedience, and ſettle them in their former Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, of which more hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>THE Worthy Sir <hi>Thomas Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kington</hi> being Sworn <hi>Lord-Mayor</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> before the <hi>Barrons</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on the <hi>29th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1689. Their Majeſties did the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:154343:47"/>City the Honour to Dine with him at their <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> where the ſight, as well as the Entertainment at a Dinner, was very Magnificent, to the high Satisfaction of all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys; and as a farther Mark of His Royal Favour, the <hi>King</hi> was pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Humble Requeſt of the <hi>Grocers</hi> Company, to permit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be Choſe Soveraign Maſter of it; and was Preſented with an Inſtrument of his Election, and a Copy of his Freedom in a Box of <hi>Gold;</hi> for which he was pleaſed to return them his thanks, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd the Honour of <hi>Knighthood</hi> on <hi>Ralph Box,</hi> their Upper-Warden; and in the <hi>Evening,</hi> upon Their Majeſties Return, the Windows were every where as they paſſed filled with Illuminations, and the Shouts of the people Proclaimed their Reſentments of the Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour done them.</p>
            <p>WHILST theſe things paſſed in <hi>England,</hi> the Joyful News came,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:154343:48"/>that the Enemy had been Beaten off, or obliged to Raiſe the Siege of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> after it had been hard preſſed a long time by a Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Army, in which the Late <hi>King</hi> was to encourage them with his preſence, but it availed not, for though the Beſieged en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the greateſt extremitys of Famine, yet by their own Valour and the Indefatigable Induſtry of Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> whom they had Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen their Governour they ſecured that Important place, for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> when the <hi>Papiſts</hi> had poſſeſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of almoſt all the other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and with <hi>French, Iriſh</hi> and others, had compoſed a very Numerous Army in the Field; but god who always takes Care for the Protection of Good <hi>Princes,</hi> and their Intereſts, gave this as a happy preſage, what wonders His Providence was about to bring to paſs.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:154343:48"/>
            <p>THE Pious <hi>Queen</hi> was not a little concerned at the Miſeries of the Poor Diſtreſſed Proteſtants, who fled as they could find Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, into <hi>England,</hi> from the Outrages of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as fearing a Cloud of <hi>Blood</hi> hung over them, ready to break on them in another <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> and by Her Bountiful Example, and Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they were very much Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and Succoured, for indeed many of the better as well as the lower condition of People, being Strip'd and Plunder'd of all they had, were become fit Objects to move compaſſion and charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them; nor failed they of Publick as well as Private Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to support their Neceſſitys, till they could be reſtored to what they were Diveſted of in their own Countrey, for Adhering to their Religion, and Their Majeſties Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, which upon the going over of the Duke of <hi>Schomberg,</hi> with
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:154343:49"/>an Army, ſoon Encreaſed, and thoſe that had beeen good at Plundring proved but very indifferent at Fighting; ſo that a great many Towns were quickly recovered, and upon the Winter Encampment, of Their Majeſties Forces on the Plains of <hi>Dundalk &amp;c.</hi> The Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys Fury Abated, and their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings were altogether at a ſtand; and ſo at this Time ſtood Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</p>
            <p>AND now, for the Bleſſings that had been ſhowered on theſe <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> in a plentiful manner, and for the further Imploring the Almightys Aſſiſtance, to proſper the finiſhing of a Work ſo well begun, Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties <hi>Proclamation</hi> was Iſſued forth for the Religious Obſerving of a <hi>Faſt,</hi> on the <hi>12th.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> and every third <hi>Wedneſday</hi> in the <hi>Month</hi> till his Majeſty, who now purpoſed to go for <hi>Ireland,</hi> Return'd. And the firſt <hi>Parliament</hi> being Deſolved, another met, on the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:154343:49"/>1690. And the King ſignifying to them, that intending to paſs the Seas, where his Preſcence was nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſary for the Reducing of <hi>Ireland,</hi> he thought it Neceſſary to leave the <hi>Government,</hi> during his abſence, in the Queens Hands: Then an Act was paſſed to Impower Her to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the Affairs of Government till his Return. And on the <hi>14th.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> 1690. the King Landed, with a Royal Army, at <hi>Carickfergus</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which brought ſuch a terror upon the Enemy, that they began to Retire in all parts of the Frontiers, but were cloſely followed, and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to an Engagement, which they declined as much as poſſible.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Queen</hi> Mannaging Affairs at home, with all that Conduct which became a Wiſe and Virtuous Princeſs. The <hi>Navy Royal</hi> being at Sea, under the Command of the Earl of <hi>Torringion, Admiral,</hi> the <hi>French King,</hi> hoping ſome great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from the Kings Abſence, or
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:154343:50"/>to Encourage the <hi>Iriſh Army,</hi> whoſe little Courage began to droop, ſet forth a very conſiderable Fleet, the greateſt we may ſay that has been ſeen of that Nation on the Seas. But the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sea-men diſdaining to Fear, being, on the contrary, full of <hi>Courage:</hi> On the <hi>30th.</hi> of <hi>June</hi> the two <hi>Navys</hi> drew up in Lines, off of <hi>Beachy;</hi> and about Nine in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the <hi>Dutch</hi> having the <hi>Van-Guard</hi> gained the <hi>Weather-Gage</hi> of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and falling on Fought very bravely for three Hours, which made thoſe they Engaged with hear away with all the Tack they could make. But about One a <hi>Clam</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening, prevented the <hi>Dutch</hi> from purſuing the Advantage they had gained, and the <hi>French,</hi> hindred by that <hi>Calm,</hi> were conſtrained to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the Fight again, which, with Extraordinary Fury, continued till Five in the Afternoon. But for what Reaſon the <hi>Engliſh Admiral</hi> not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to Second them, as they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:154343:50"/>we determin not, for but a few <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships, who were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on by the Courage of their Captains Engaging the Main Body of the <hi>French</hi> falling into the Rear of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> they were ſo Batter'd that they ſound themſelves conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to make their way thorough the <hi>French</hi> Fleet, and ſtand for the Coaſt of <hi>England,</hi> between <hi>Beverſire</hi> and <hi>Farly,</hi> looſing divers Officers of Note, and ſeveral of their Ships Burnt by the Enemy; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' the <hi>French</hi> Fleet conſiſted of 82 <hi>Men of War,</hi> beſides <hi>Fireſhips,</hi> and <hi>Tenders,</hi> and ours was Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to them in <hi>Number;</hi> has we had a <hi>Drake</hi> to our Admiral, they had no doubt run the ſame Riſque, as the <hi>Spaniſh Armado</hi> did, in 1588 but what was done could not then be recalled, yet was ſoon after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed with ſuch a ſtroak, as made all <hi>France</hi> tremble at the unwelcome <hi>Bonfires</hi> that were made on their <hi>Coaſts,</hi> by the Renowned Admiral <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> as will appear in the <hi>Sequel.</hi>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:154343:51"/>For this Defect Admiral <hi>Torrington was ſent to the Tower,</hi> and afterward Tryed on Board the <hi>Kent</hi> in the River <hi>Medway,</hi> but had the Fortune to be Acquitted, and the <hi>French</hi> upon the retiring of our Fleet having Burnt a few <hi>Fiſhers Cottages</hi> at <hi>Tinmouth,</hi> and there hearing the <hi>Militia</hi> of the counties of <hi>England,</hi> were for the moſt part in <hi>Arms,</hi> they durſt Adventure no further, but returned to their Ships; and after a little Hovering about the <hi>Coaſt,</hi> and Stealing a few <hi>Sheep</hi> out of the <hi>Marſhes</hi> went home, making a mighty boaſt of a Victory that they had not Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THIS</hi> however little availed their Confederates in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the King (though as he was view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Enemies <hi>Camp</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Wound on the Shoulder with a great Shot) paſſing the River <hi>Boyne,</hi> fell upon their Army with ſuch Bravery that Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:154343:51"/>they far out numbred him he put them to the Rout in all parts in leſs than three Hours, whole Regiments running away without being charged, as appeared by their Arms found on the Ground in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimental Order; whereupon the Late King <hi>James</hi> within a Day or two took <hi>Shipping,</hi> and Sailed for <hi>France</hi> upon this <hi>Dublin</hi> Opened her Gates, and moſt of the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Towns in thoſe parts ſoon after Surrendred, and the Countys that had been long Hazarded, were ſetled and found Eaſe and Peace.</p>
            <p>THIS News cauſed rejoycings in <hi>England,</hi> whilſt the <hi>Queen</hi> with great Conduct and Prudence, mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the <hi>Kings</hi> Abſence, the weighty affairs of the Kingdom, carrying her ſelf with ſuch a Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Conſtancy as Daunted the boldeſt repiner at her Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. The <hi>Militia</hi> was raiſed, the <hi>Coaſt</hi> Guarded, and a ſtrict Eye had
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:154343:52"/>over thoſe ſuſpected to be diſſaffect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Government, and care every where taken by Her Majeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys Order, for the Security of the Peace and Quiet of the Kingdom, ſo that the people were not only free from all conſternations and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of Danger, but on the contrary full of Courage, and Smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Diſdain, on the weak at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts and bravado's of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys. The <hi>Trained Bands</hi> of <hi>London</hi> with much Gallantry, Chearfulneſs, and Reſolution, March'd into <hi>Hide Par,</hi> and Drew up in a Splendid Appearance, to the number of 10000 Effectual Men, compleatly Armed, and Appointed, and there Her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty was pleaſed to be preſent, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a view of them whilſt they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, approving of their ready<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Loyalty at ſuch a junct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure; and by her preſence gave them the higheſt ſatisfaction Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, which they expreſſed in their Reſolves, <hi>To Live and Dye,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:154343:52"/>in her Defence,</hi> againſt all Invaders or <hi>Clandeſtine</hi> Enemies, but there being to further occaſion at that time, they returned home in the ſame Excellent Order they had Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched thither, and all things remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtill and quiet; and both ours and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet, were Recruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gallantly in a little time.</p>
            <p>SOON after this Her Majeſty received News that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had Beaten the <hi>French</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on St. <hi>Chriſtophers,</hi> and Siezed the greateſt part of the <hi>Booty</hi> in the <hi>Iſland,</hi> and Divers <hi>French</hi> Merchant Ships of conſiderable Burthen and Richly Laden, were taken by our Privateers and <hi>Men of War,</hi> for the Fleet was again at Sea, and ſoon after to repair what had before happened, ſet Sail for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and was mainly aſſiſting in the taking of <hi>Cork</hi> and <hi>Kingſail:</hi> and the Kings Returning after His Glorious Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs created great Joy and thanks, for the wonderful Mercy and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:154343:53"/>in preſerving his Pretious Life from the Dangers that Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, and reſtoring to us him in health and ſafety. Upon His Majeſtys Happy Arival, after his Glorious Enterpriſe, having by his wonted Courage and Conduct in a great Meaſure Secured a Kingdom, that was at the Point of being over-run by an Enemy, who made their chief boaſt in reſolves to Root out the Proteſtant Religion, ſo long ſetled and Flouriſhing there: The Joy was not only great in the <hi>Queen</hi> and Court, but all over <hi>England,</hi> as appeared by the many Addreſſes to Congratulate his Safety, and Happy Return, &amp; Encomiums made on the Welcome Occaſion.</p>
            <p>THIS Joy ſpread wider than the narrow bounds of our <hi>Iſland,</hi> being Lively expreſſed in almoſt all the <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> And the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> finding that the <hi>French</hi> King, by large (though unjuſt) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, encroached upon his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:154343:53"/>thinking it high time to provide for the Liberty and Safety of his Subjects, before they were brought to that Diſtreſs that others had fallen into, by delay, and too much Relyance on <hi>French</hi> Flatery, and deſembled proteſtations of good meaning towards them. Being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to come into the <hi>Alyance,</hi> ſent his <hi>Envoys</hi> or <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> to the <hi>Courts</hi> of the <hi>Confederate Princes,</hi> whoſe Negotiations Concluded very Proſperouſly, Averting from him the Fate of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Burgundy, &amp;c.</hi> that had been ſo Treacherouſly taken from their Rightful Owners, whilſt they were held in hand with ſpecious pretences, that no ſuch thing was intended. And that it may, with reaſon be held, that the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Savoy</hi> is looked on as one of the Politick <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> The Expreſſions of the Sieur <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la-Tour</hi> (<hi>Baron</hi> of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of State to the <hi>Duke,</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the <hi>Finaces</hi> of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:154343:54"/>
               <hi>Intendant</hi> of his <hi>Royal Highneſſes</hi> Houſhold) delivered when he had his Audience of the King and Queen, as Envoy Extraordinary here, from the Duke, which for the Elegance of the Stile, gaining a General Approbation, may be well Inſerted here.</p>
            <p>TO the King, He Addreſſed Himſelf in the Following Words,</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>HIS Royal <hi>Highneſs</hi> Congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates Your Majeſty's Glorious Acceſs to the Crown, Due to Your Birth, Merited by Your Virtues, and Maintained by Your Valour; Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence Ordained it, for Your Sacred Head, for the Accompliſhments of Heavens Deſigns, from all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>THAT Providence (which after a long forbearance, Raiſes up Choſen Inſtruments at length, to Suppreſs Violence, and Protect Juſtice. The Wonderful, beginnings of Your Reign,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:154343:54"/>are ſure Preſages of the Bleſſing Heaven is Preparing, for the Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Your Intentions, which have no other Aim, than to Reſtore this Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Kingdom, to that Grandeur which it Antiently Enjoy'd; and to Break thoſe Chains, under the Weight of which, all <hi>Europe</hi> at Preſent Groans.</p>
               <p>THIS Magnanimous Deſign ſo Worthy, the <hi>Heroe</hi> of our Age ſoon fill'd His Royal <hi>Highneſs</hi> with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Joy, tho' He was Conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to keep it <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndiſcloſed for a Time, in the Privacy of his Heart; and if afterwards, he could not forbear to let it break forth the Obligation is Due to Your Majeſty: You have at length Inſpired him with Hopes of Liberty, after ſo many Years Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
               <p>MY Words, and the Treaty which I have already Signed at the <hi>Hague,</hi> with Your Majeſty<hi>'s Envoy,</hi> but faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Expreſs my Maſters Paſſionate Deſires, to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite himſelf to Your
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:154343:55"/>
                  <hi>Majeſty</hi> by an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nviolable Devotion to Your Service.</p>
               <p>THE Honour which he has of being one that appertains to Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, has Knit the firſt Knot of this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and the Protection You Grant him with ſo much Generoſity has brought it to the Perfection of being Indiſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable. Theſe are the ſincere Sente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Royal Highneſs, with which I dare not Preſume to intermix any thing of my own, for how Ardent ſoever my Zeal may be, how Profound ſoever my Veneration of Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtys Glory, I know not how better to expreſs, it, than by the Silence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and Admiration,</p>
            </q>
            <p>BY this Speech, we ſee how a Good <hi>Prince,</hi> gains not only the Love and Entire Affections of his own Subjects, but even that of all Generous <hi>Princes</hi> and Good Men; and Raiſes to himſelf Trophies in their Hearts, that ſhall ſtand as Laſting Monuments of his Worth and Renown.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:154343:55"/>
            <p>AFTER this Eloquent Speech made to the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Envoy</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed himſelf to the <hi>Queen,</hi> in the Following Words. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>MADAM,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>VIRT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E at the ſame time with Your Majeſty Aſcended to the Throne, and all <hi>Europe</hi> beheld it with Admiration, but the Effects have been to none more Joyfully Grateful than to his Royal <hi>Highneſs,</hi> whilſt You have the Goodneſs to be the Support of his Concerns, and he the Honour to Depend ſo nearly on Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
               <p>I Return Your Majeſty moſt Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thanks on his Behalf, and beg Your Protection, of a <hi>Prince</hi> moſt Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently Aſſured, That he ſhall ſtill up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Dignity of his high Degree, if Heaven Vouchſafe to Support the Juſtice of his Cauſe, by the <hi>King's</hi> Valour, Your <hi>Majeſty's</hi> Prudence; which You made appear the Laſt Summer, after a moſt Wonderful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:154343:56"/>not only Winning the Hearts of Your Subjects by the Mildneſs of Your Government, but Striking a Terror in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Your Enemies, by the Conſtancy of Your Courage.</p>
               <p>THIS is a Felicity that will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways attend Your Majeſtys Heroick Virtues, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite to Your Immortal Glory, the Eternal Happineſs of Your Kingdoms. And this <hi>Madam,</hi> I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together Wiſh, with a Fervent Zeal, as the Moſt Faithful of Your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
            </q>
            <p>HERE we find the beſt of <hi>Queens,</hi> Admired almoſt to Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, by thoſe who in a manner had only heard of her <hi>Virtues, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety,</hi> and <hi>Prudent Conduct</hi> in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging the Great and Weighty affair of the Kingdom, in the <hi>Kings</hi> Abſence, when the <hi>French</hi> were on the <hi>Coaſt,</hi> and in other matters as has been ſhewed before. Her Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cys and Tender Compaſſions to the Oppreſſed, have been Worthily, but can never ſufficiently be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:154343:56"/>The Wiſdom of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were ſenſible of this, and the <hi>Commons</hi> Aſſembled in <hi>Parliament</hi> having Addreſſed the <hi>King</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate his Succeſs, and Happy Preſervation; Addreſſed the <hi>Queen</hi> in this Humble Tender of their Affections to her Royal Perſon, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>May it Pleaſe Your Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WE Your Moſt Dutiful and Loyal Subjects, the <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> Aſſembled, do Moſt Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg leave to Expreſs the Deep ſenſe we have of the Goodneſs Wiſdom, and Courage, which Your Majeſty did Manifeſt in the Greateſt Difficulties, and moſt. Preſſing Dangers, during His Majeſtys Abſence at a time, when a Powerful Enemy was upon the Coaſt, when the Nation was weakned in that part, which is its proper Strength and Deprived of the Security of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties preſence. The Reſolution Your
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:154343:57"/>Majeſty Shewed in Your Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, gave Life to Your Subjects and made them excert a Strength and Force, unknown to the former Reigns, and Your Zeal for the Publick En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged them to ſhew ſuch Chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their Duty, as Diſappointed the Hopes and Deſigns of all the Open and Secret Enemies of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>THE Grateful Remembrance of this, which Renews the Remembrance of our moſt Happy Times, will for ever Remain in the Hearts of Your People, and can never fail to be Expreſſed in all Inſtances of Loyalty and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience from us and all the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>SO much the Goodneſs and Sweetneſs of Temper in the <hi>Queen,</hi> had wound her into the Hearts of Her People, that no Expreſſions of Gratitude could be wanting to make an Acknowledgment of the Tranquility we enjoyed under her Auſpicious Government and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:154343:57"/>ſo Mild and ſecure, that it appeared a <hi>Halcyon</hi> Calm to other Reigns, in which the Bluſtring Storms of <hi>State</hi> proved very Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent and uneaſy to a great part of the Nation, ſo that the People ſhewed a Ready willingneſs in all the Sums that were given by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in Freely parting with their Money for the Support of the Royal <hi>Dignity,</hi> and carrying on a War, againſt our Profeſſed <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemys.</hi> Proviſion was likewiſe made with the greateſt <hi>Celerity</hi> Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable for Building Ships of War, Raiſing Forces, and what ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides was Requiſite, for Agrandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the Fame and Reputation of Their Majeſties, and their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms: So that a Greater Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the minds of the Generality of Men, was never obſerved in this Nation.</p>
            <p>AND now the <hi>Princes</hi> abroad in Alliance, and Confederated in the War againſt <hi>France,</hi> reſolving
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:154343:58"/>on a General <hi>Congreſs</hi> at the <hi>Hague,</hi> to <hi>Concert</hi> Affairs, and ſettle mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for the Vigorous Proſecution of their enterprize, and His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> finding his Preſence very Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in that <hi>Grand</hi> Aſſembly, min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Parliament of it in a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Speech, and Deſired them to <hi>haſten the matters before them,</hi> which accordingly they did with all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient ſpeed, and divers <hi>Acts</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Royal <hi>Aſſent,</hi> very much conducing to the Advantage of the Government. And ſo both Houſes having <hi>Adjourned</hi> for ſome time, the <hi>King</hi> took leave of the <hi>Queen,</hi> and <hi>Court,</hi> and with ſome Difficulty, by reaſon of the <hi>Ice,</hi> he notwithſtanding all Difficulty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Landed Safe, Attended by His Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> the Lord <hi>Steward,</hi> Lord <hi>Chamberlain,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Portland</hi> and <hi>Monmouth,</hi> Sieurs <hi>Overkirk,</hi> and <hi>Zuleſtein;</hi> and going from <hi>Oram-Haak,</hi> near <hi>Maſe-Landſluys,</hi> the place where they came
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:154343:58"/>on Shoar to <hi>Hounſlyr-Dyke;</hi> the Deputys of the <hi>States</hi> Ordered to that Purpoſe, Attended on His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to Welcome him, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate his Happy Arival, and ſo paſſing to the <hi>Hague,</hi> the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Council of State,</hi> with the <hi>Heads</hi> of <hi>the Colledges,</hi> made their Complements to him.</p>
            <p>AND here a Grateful Nations Joy appeared in the moſt Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Manner; Divers Stately Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Triumph being placed in the chief parts of the Town, with <hi>Motto's</hi> and <hi>Devices,</hi> ſuitable to the great Occaſion. And the <hi>Evening</hi> concluded with <hi>Fire-Works, Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,</hi> and all the Demonſtrations that might Render it Acceptable. And divers <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates</hi> being there, they Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Conſult of the Weighty Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, that concerned the Good and Intereſt of all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> which was then ſetled in the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as the Product and Iſſue of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:154343:59"/>thoſe happy Councils have ſince manifeſted to the World.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Queen</hi> having again the Government in her Hands, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Kings</hi> Abſence, manag'd it with that Prudence and Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which made the Nation ſee, how much it was beholden to ſo Excellent a <hi>Princeſs:</hi> Our Secret and Forreign Enemys, who labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to take Advantages on all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, found their Deſigns fruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated, and all their Dark Pollicys countermined, and thoſe miſchiefs they deſigned others, turned upon themſelves, though in their Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, ſome of them found Mercy beyond their Expectations, from thoſe who prefer it to Juſtice, from a <hi>Queen</hi> who was all Mercy and Compaſſion, and a <hi>King</hi> whoſe Virtues and Heroick Spirit moved him to Compaſſionute even his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemys, who had Cauſleſly made themſelves to their Detriment and Hazzard of their Lives; but paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:154343:59"/>this over, we proceed to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of more weight and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>King</hi> returning from the <hi>Congreſs,</hi> after the Happy ſetling of Affairs, was received with Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Rejoycings of the People: And by the Pious <hi>Queen</hi> with ſuch Joy, that is beyond our Expreſſion. And having ſetled Affairs, with Wonderful Prudence here; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces paſſing over to <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> he delayed not to be at the Head of them, and with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſo Encouraged and Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Spirits of the Army, that all things Succeeded beyond what many Expected. So that the <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign</hi> ended Succeſsfully, and gave us an earneſt of what have been ſince Evident to the World; and the <hi>Queen</hi> had the Grateful thanks and acknowledgment of her Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for her Prudence and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in the Management of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and in Her Royal Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:154343:60"/>Goodneſs and Modeſty, expreſſed Her Self Glad, that She had done any thing that Pleaſed Her People. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>WINTER being Come, Great Preparations at Home and Abroad were made, againſt the Opening the <hi>Campaign,</hi> for the Year 1692. The <hi>Fleet</hi> was <hi>Equip'd</hi> very early; The Honourable <hi>Admiral Ruſſel,</hi> Commanding it, under whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, the <hi>Seamen</hi> were very much Revived, in their Courage and Reſolution. Nor did the <hi>Dutch</hi> delay to Joyn ours, with a very Gallant Squadron of <hi>Ships</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> Reſolute to Revenge the Injurys they had Suſtained the preceding Year: And all things here went Succeſsfully on. Whilſt the <hi>King</hi> was preparing to Purſue his Vict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ories Abroad, <hi>Scotland</hi> had entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gained the upper hand of its Enemys; and <hi>Ireland,</hi> under the Conduct of Lievtenant General <hi>Ginkle,</hi> and other Brave Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:154343:60"/>was Reduced, and Owned its Rightful Soveraign; of which Proceedings we ſhall give a further Account hereafter.</p>
            <p>THE Nation at this time was full of Spirit, and that antient Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age revived in it, that has for many Ages been renowned through the World. Providence concurring with our deſires, to make us a Proſperous and Happy People in ſpight of all Opoſers, either open or clandeſtine. The beſt of <hi>Queens,</hi> by her influence, adding new Life and Vigour to her Loyal and deſervedly affected Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and like a guiding Star, lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or directing them to their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. She Aroſe like another <hi>Debora,</hi> a Mother in our <hi>IſrAel,</hi> to relieve her Kingdoms from Opreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and make them flouriſh; that after our Calamities, we might hear of Joy and Rejoycing, That the Rains being over, and the Winter paſt, the fragrant Flowers of proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity might appear in our Land:
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:154343:61"/>Whilſt the noyſe of the <hi>Turtle</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed us the Springing up from the Field of War, a Bleſſed Crop of a continued and laſting Peace; when thoſe that have Diſturb'd it ſhall be compelled to do reaſon; and like a <hi>Cormorant</hi> be conſtrained to diſgorge in a little time, what he has been ſo long a ſwallowing. Providence to this Nation has been always kind; and that watchful Fate that Guards the Virtuous will, no doubt, gain the Aſcendant over their Enemys.</p>
            <p>THE Fleet, as we have ſaid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bravely Equiped, and the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men full of Courage, nothing was wanting but on whom to expreſs their Valour; and ſhew the World that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have not their Epethite, of <hi>Lords of the Ocean,</hi> in vain; and indeed there was not an Enemy long wanting, for the <hi>French,</hi> either being deceived in the number of our Ships, or in hopes only our ſinall Frigats were abroad, or that being otherways gulled by
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:154343:61"/>falſe Intelligence, that there might be a Defect in our Fleet, tending to a Revolt of ſome part of it: They put to Sea, under <hi>Monſieur Tourville</hi> their Admiral, in Search of ours, who were very deſirous of finding them; and in Concluſion gave them ſuch a welcome, as they had never before received on the <hi>Brittiſh Ocean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Dreadful Scene of <hi>War</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, which Scattered the Toſſing Billows with the Wracks of our Oppoſers, and made the Watery <hi>Fry,</hi> Tremble at the Repeated Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of our Terreſtial Thunder. Our Guardian Angel now Commiſſioned by Omnipotence, Scatter'd Death and Deſtruction Round him, and Crimſon'd the Rumpled Waves with <hi>Bloud;</hi> but not to Elaborate on this Great and Glorious Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which otherwiſe expreſſes it ſelf in a Gloomy Terror to our Foes, we ſhall procceed to give the Reader an Account of the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:154343:62"/>moſt Material Matters that happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on this great Occaſion, on which the Ballance of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo mainly Depended. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>French</hi> Thinking to do great Matters at Sea this Summer, got their Fleet out ſomewhat ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than they were wont, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more numerous and daring than they did the laſt Summer; ſo that on the 9th of <hi>May,</hi> their whole Fleet, was, about Noon, ſeen off of <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> at a great Diſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> three Leagues from the Start, and continued turning to the Eaſtward, the Wind at Eaſt and by North; and the next Day, they were again ſeen from the ſame place, when, by their ſailing, they ſeemed as if they intended to ſtand to their own Coaſt: And our Fleet being now well mann'd, and in a very good Readineſs on the 14th of <hi>May,</hi> in the Afternoon, Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> weighed Anchor out of <hi>Rye Bay,</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:154343:62"/>and about eleven the next Morning joyned Sir <hi>Ralph Delaval,</hi> and Rear Admiral <hi>Carter</hi> at St. <hi>Helens,</hi> and ſoon after divers Dutch Men of War joyn'd him, ſo that the whole Fleet conſiſted of about Ninety Sail of Ships for the Line of Battel, the Officers and Seamen being very hearty and full of Courage, and every thing gave a happy Preſage of the Glorious Succeſs that ſoon after enſued, as appears by the Loyal Addreſs, humbly preſented to Her Majeſty by the Chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of her Fleet; which for the Satisfaction of the Reader, it may not be amiſs to Inſert, as an Introduction to ſo glorious an Enterprize. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Queen being informed of a ſcandalous and malitious Report that was ſpread abroad, as if ſome of the Officers of their Majeſties Fleet were diſaffected, or not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in their Service, and that her Majeſty had thereupon ordered the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:154343:63"/>Diſcharge of many of them from their Employments; Her Majeſty was pleaſed to command the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Nottingham</hi> to write to Admiral <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> and let him know, that Her Majeſty was ſatisfied that this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port was raiſed by the Enemies of the Govenment, and that ſhe repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo entire a Confidence in their Fidelity, that ſhe had reſolved not to diſplace any one of them; which being by the Admiral communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, they made and ſent up the following Addreſs.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>WE Your Majeſtys moſt dutiful and loyal Subjects and Servants, Flag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Officers and Captains in Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Fleet; out of the deep and grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Senſe we have of Your Majeſty's good and juſt Opinion of our Loyalty and Fidelity Imparted to us by the Right Honourable Admiral <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> in a Letter to him from my Lord <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham,</hi> do, in the behalf of our ſelves, and all other Officers and Seamen,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:154343:63"/>preſume to addreſs our ſelves, to your Majeſty at this Juncture, to undeceive the World in thoſe falſe and malitious Reports that have been lately ſpread in Prejudice of Your Majeſty's Service, by People of an unreaſonable Diſaffection to Your Majeſty's Government, and an obſtinate Averſion to the Quiet and Good of our Country, that there are ſome amongſt us that are not truly zealous for, and entirely devoted to your Maieſty's Service; we do therefore moſt humbly beg Your Majeſty's Leave to add to our repeated Oaths, this Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our Fidelity, that we with all imaginable Alacrity and Reſolution, venture our Lives in the Defence of Your Majeſty's undoubted Rights and the Liberty and Religion of our Country, againſt all Forreign and Popiſh Invaders whatſoever; and that God Almighty may preſerve Your Majeſty's moſt ſacred Perſon, direct your Counſils, and proſper Your Arms by Sea and Land againſt Your Majeſty's Enemies, Let
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:154343:64"/>all the People ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> with Your Majeſty's Dutiful and Loyal Subjects.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated on Board the <hi>Britania,</hi> 
                        <date>May <hi>15.</hi> 1692.</date> at St. <hi>Helens.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THIS was ſigned by Sir <hi>John Aſhby,</hi> Admiral of the Red, Mr. <hi>Rook,</hi> vice Admiral of the Blew, Sir <hi>Clouſly Shovel,</hi> Rear-Admiral of the Red; Mr. <hi>Carter,</hi> Rear-Admiral of the Blew; upon receiving which, her Majeſty was pleaſed to ſay, <hi>That ſhe had always this Opinion of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, but was glad this was come to ſatisfie others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Dutch and Engliſh Fleets being Joyned on the 18 of <hi>May</hi> the Admirals Scout, gave the ſigne for ſeeing the Enemy about the grey or opening of the Morning, our Fleet made the <hi>French</hi> Fleet in a Line of Battel, about two Leagues to the Windward; and they then having the weather-gage, bore down very boldly and cloſely upon our Fleet;
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:154343:64"/>at Eleven the Engagement began, and continued very hot and furious till almoſt four in the Afternoon, at what time the <hi>French</hi> Eleet bore away. The Wind at Weſt, and South and by Eaſt, and North North Eaſt, Sir <hi>Clouſly Shovel,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Aſhby,</hi> having the weather-gage, fell bravely on, maintaining the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment till almoſt ten at Night; the <hi>French</hi> all that while bearing away, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> purſuing them, ſome Ships were ſeen in the Night-time in flames, about nine of the Clock;</p>
            <p>UPON this News, and ever to be wiſh'd for Succeſs, as well by Land as Sea, of which heaven has given us already ſo great an Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of future Improvement againſt the Common Enemy, not only the Joy of all Good Subjects Abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the Bells, in all Places where it came, were Rung out; the Tower Guns, and thoſe in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, were diſcharged, and the Streets at Night, filled with
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:154343:65"/>
               <hi>Bonfires</hi> and <hi>Illuminations,</hi> to the great Contentment and Rejoycing of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Killingſworth,</hi> Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the <hi>Fox Fire-Ship,</hi> made his way to <hi>Portſmouth</hi> in his Boat; and gave an Account, that he had Burnt his Fire-ſhip on Board the <hi>French</hi> Rear-Admiral, but was put off with a great deal of difficulty; and that he ſaw a <hi>French</hi> Man of War, of about Seventy Guns, Blow up, and another <hi>Three-Deck'd</hi> Ship on Fire.</p>
            <p>ON the Twenty-firſt, about Nine of the Clock in the Morning, our Fleet ſet Sail again; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe did the <hi>French:</hi> Admiral <hi>Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> took his Courſe towards <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleur,</hi> having got ſight of Divers Ships under the Shoar: Admiral <hi>Allemond,</hi> of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and the Admiral of the Blew, Sailed to the <hi>Weſtward.</hi> The Firſt of theſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to get up with Sixteen of the Enemies Ships, which he Diſcovered, Suppoſing them to be
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:154343:65"/>coming from <hi>France</hi> to Joyn the <hi>French</hi> Fleet. Sir <hi>John Aſhby</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued the reſt of the <hi>French</hi> Fleet, who in much confuſion laboured to get into the <hi>Raſe</hi> of <hi>Ornay.</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Allemond</hi> loſt Sight of the Aforementioned Sixteen Ships in the Night, they having (as he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) got in among the Rocks; and becauſe he found it not Safe, nor Convenient to Follow them there, he Sailed <hi>Eaſtward</hi> again to Rejoyn <hi>Admiral Ruſſel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ON the Twenty-Second in the Morning, Vice-Admiral <hi>Delaval</hi> Burnt, near to the <hi>Shoar,</hi> under <hi>Cape de Wike,</hi> a great Ship, called the <hi>Riſing Sun,</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> being the Ship of Count <hi>De Tourville,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Admiral, carrying a Hundred and Four Guns; as likewiſe the Admiral commanded by his <hi>Second,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Beaujeu,</hi> a Ship carrying a Hundred and two Guns; and the <hi>Fort</hi> of Eighty Guns; with two Frigates, and three of leſſer rank. The Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:154343:66"/>who were taken from the burnt Ships, declared, That during the time of the Battle, Four or Five of their biggeſt Ships were deſtroyed. Reer-Admiral <hi>Carter,</hi> and Collonel <hi>Haſtings,</hi> after much Bravery and Reſolution, were both killed in the Fight. Admiral <hi>Ruſſell,</hi> before <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bogue,</hi> the <hi>23d</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> ordered Vice-Admiral <hi>Rook,</hi> with a Squadron of Ships, being the ſmaller Men of War, and Fire-Ships, and all the Boats in the Fleet mann'd with Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, with Fire-Arms, to ſet fire to thoſe <hi>French</hi> Ships which lay before them, penn'd up by our great Men of War: It pleaſed God to bleſs their enterprize ſo well, that that Night, Six of their Ships were ſet on Fire, and utterly Deſtroyed; and the next Morning Six more Run the ſame Fate; with one that Overſet, and was Entirely loſt; Six of theſe being Capitals of Three Decks, from Seventy to Ninety Guns, and upwards; the others,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:154343:66"/>from Sixty to Seventy: Our Men in the Boats behaving themſelves ſo Bravely, that they Boarded them, and made their own Guns Fire up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Platforms on Shoar, Beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Enemys therefrom, where they were in great Confuſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding their Ruin, in the Deſtuct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of their Ships. Thus it has Pleaſed God, of his Infinite Mercy, ſo to Bleſs the Arms of Their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſties, that thoſe that Threatned <hi>England</hi> with an Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and utter Ruin, may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of their Miſtake, and feel the Effect themſelves; of which, we hope, this is an Happy Omen. Thus have we given you an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Deſtruction of their Principal <hi>Men of War.</hi> For which we ought to Bleſs God, that hath brought their Great Deſigns to Naught, and Confounded their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize, and Preſerv'd <hi>England,</hi> as he hath done heretofore in 1588. in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:154343:67"/>
            <p>THESE Blazing Fires on the Coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> proved very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome, not only Affrighting thoſe who were Spectators from the Shoar, but made even <hi>Paris</hi> Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Drew a <hi>Curtain</hi> of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy</hi> over the Pleaſures at the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Verſalies,</hi> when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templated how much their once un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded hopes had been ſet back, or fruſtrated, this and the Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Year: How they had altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loſt their Footing in <hi>Ireland:</hi> For the King of <hi>Englands</hi> intent upon the Great Affairs in <hi>Flanders,</hi> having appointed the Barron <hi>D' Ginkle,</hi> his Lievtenant General, in the before mentioned Kingdom; <hi>Ballymore</hi> with little reſiſtance Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred; <hi>Athlone</hi> was taken by Storm; and a Formidable <hi>Army,</hi> Compoſed of <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Routed and Diſperſed, at <hi>Agbrim,</hi> St. <hi>Ruth</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral being Kill'd in the beginning of the Battle; <hi>Galloway</hi> ſoon after was
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:154343:67"/>gained; and laſtly <hi>Lymerick</hi> when it had endured a Conſiderable Siege, Vigorouſly carry'd on, Capitulated upon Articles, and upon the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render of it, all the <hi>Iriſh</hi> according to that Capitulation, returned to their Obedience, except ſuch as were Decoy'd to <hi>France.</hi> And as a Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phey of this Succeſs, reſtoring a Kingdom to its Trade, and Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing State; the <hi>Banners</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns</hi> taken at <hi>Aghrim,</hi> were placed for ſome time in St. <hi>James's</hi> Park, by <hi>Whitehall,</hi> to ſhow Heavens Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in the Juſtneſs of Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Arms, and the Swiftneſs of the Victorys obtained, for which, and the Great Defeat at Sea, <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> expreſſed her Joy in all ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able demonſtrations.</p>
            <p>AND that we might make due Returns to Almighty God, whoſe Hand had ſo Signally appeared in all our Proceedings, Prayers and Praiſes, were put up for his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Mercys and Deliverances.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:154343:68"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Campaign</hi> for this Year, concluding in <hi>Flanders,</hi> His Majeſtys Return was Congratulated with all the Demonſtrations a Loyal Nation was capable of expreſſing in Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to a <hi>Prince,</hi> who had Hazzarded ſo much for their Safety, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. And Affairs being ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and in an Almoſt unexpected quiet, throughout the Three <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi> by Their Majeſties Prudence and Conduct, the <hi>Alliance</hi> abroad being firmly fixed. The <hi>King</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted again from <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and with a Proſperous Gail, paſſed over to <hi>Holland,</hi> where he was Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with the uſual Expreſſions of Joy, and all the Tender Reſpect of a Willing and Grateful People, whoſe Safety his Anceſtors, and his own Heroick Virtues, Courage and Conduct, had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſerved and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the Settlement of their Government, Trade, and Liberties <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT long he Stayed not, after
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:154343:68"/>he had Received the Complements and Congratulations of <hi>Holland,</hi> before he paſſed to the Camp in <hi>Flanders,</hi> to give what Orders were Neceſſary for Oppoſing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the Common Enemy.</p>
            <p>During theſe Tranſactions the Affairs in <hi>England</hi> were in a Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous Condition; the <hi>Queens</hi> Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in all her management of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, ſcarcely admitting of a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in her Sex. The <hi>Fleet</hi> was Equiped and all things Ordered in the moſt Excellent manner: The Courage of the Seamen, was as great as ever, and our Land For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces being Drawn out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that Kingdom being entirely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, as has been already mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, were the better at Leiſure, to give the <hi>French</hi> King a Diverſion nearer Home, who had ſent his Troops ſo far, to Diſturb a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to which he had not the leaſt Pretenſion or Claim; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, the Confederate <hi>Army</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:154343:69"/>ſo Formidable, that <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>14th.</hi> (tho' we had ſome News told us he deſign'd it) upon more Mature Adviſement, Ventured not into the Field, concluding the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-Muſick to be more Pleaſant and Secure, than the Noiſe of <hi>Drums</hi> and <hi>Trumpets,</hi> or Wedging into the Grim Ridges of ſuch a <hi>War,</hi> in Perſon, by which we perceive the difference in <hi>Princes,</hi> and ought to know how to eſteem a Bleſſing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Hand of Heaven, as a Sheltring Shield to Protect us, with ſo much Undaunted Bravery and Reſolution.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Merchants</hi> ſo encouraged, ſet out a great many Gallant Ships, to Trade in divers parts of the Trading World; and amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the <hi>Turkey</hi> Fleet, with a conſiderable Convoy of <hi>Men of War,</hi> under the Command of Sir <hi>George Rook,</hi> Sailed; our Main Fleet ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them about Fifty Leagues <hi>W. S. W.</hi> off of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhant,</hi> were they
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:154343:69"/>parted with Sir <hi>George,</hi> on the 6th of <hi>June,</hi> not having ſeen or heard of the <hi>Enemys</hi> Fleet; yet in the <hi>Streights</hi> they unexpectedly fell in with them, not having before any certain Advice where they were. However, ſuch was the Courage and Prudence of ours, and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Commanders, as well <hi>Merchantmen</hi> as <hi>Men of War,</hi> that the <hi>Enemy</hi> loſt their expected advantage, very few of the Ships falling into their hands, though their whole <hi>Naval</hi> Force had in a manner encompaſſed them, moſt of the <hi>Merchants</hi> Ships getting into ſafe and friendly Ports; and the <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> (after they had given them that opportunity) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Brave Retreat with divers of the reſt.</p>
            <p>AND now the City of <hi>London</hi> to expreſs the true ſenſe they had of the <hi>Queens</hi> Prudent Conduct, in the management of weighty affairs, and kindneſs to them, made their Addreſs to her, by the Hands of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:154343:70"/>the <hi>Lord Mayor, Aldermen,</hi> and <hi>Common Council,</hi> in the following Words, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the</hi> Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EENS Moſt Excellent <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WE Your Majeſty's Moſt Dutiful and Loyal Subjects, the <hi>Mayor Aldermen,</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> of the City of <hi>London,</hi> in Common Council Aſſembled; out of a Deep Senſe of the Infinite Goodneſs of God to this Nation, in the Signal Deliverance of His Sacred Majeſty, from thoſe Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, for which he hath ſo lately, for our Sakes, expoſed his Royal Perſon even to the Admiration of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys. Do Heartily and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfeignedly in the firſt place, return to Almighty God, our moſt Humble Thanks; and in the next, in all Humility, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate Your Majeſty, upon ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>enſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Providence as the Preſervation of that <hi>Prince,</hi> in whoſe Life, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our Laws, and Religion, but the Liberty of <hi>Europe</hi> is ſo entirely wrap'd up.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:154343:70"/>
AND Your <hi>Majeſty</hi> having been ſo Graciouſly Pleaſed, by the <hi>Lord Keeper,</hi> to ſignifie the Deep Senſe of the great Loſſes at Sea, which have befallen the Traders of this City and Kingdom: And the Directions Your <hi>Majeſty</hi> has given, to the Committee of Your <hi>Majeſty's</hi> Moſt Honour able Privy Council, as well to Examine into the Cauſes of ſuch Misfortunes, as to take Effectual Care to prevent the like for the future; by encouraging Your <hi>Majeſty's</hi> Subjects to make their Application to the ſaid Committee. We do with all Chearfulneſs Render Our Hearty Thanks to Your Moſt Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Majeſty,</hi> for ſo great a Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; in no wiſe Doubting, but Your <hi>Majeſty</hi> will continue to give ſuch Good and Seaſonable Directions; that the Trade of this Your Kingdom, in which the Proſperity of it doth ſo much depend, may be better Supported for the future.</p>
                  <p>AND as we have hitherto from a Senſe of our Duty, Demonſtrated
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:154343:71"/>to the World our Great Zeal for Your <hi>Majeſty's</hi> Service; we having now a freſh Opportunity of ſhewing the ſame, by the Chearful and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimous ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing of Money, for the Preſent Emergencies of Your <hi>Majeſty's</hi> affairs. Humbly Beg Leave to Aſſure Your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> of our firm Reſolution to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue our Hearty Endeavours, upon all Occaſions, to ſupport Your <hi>Majeſty's</hi> Royal Authority and Government, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Perſons, to the utmoſt of our Power.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THIS was received by the Queen with very Gracious Expreſſions, highly Satisfactory to thoſe that Preſented it, who as a farther mark of Her Favour had the Honour of Kiſſing Her Hand.</p>
            <p>SOON after a <hi>Proclamation</hi> was Publiſhed, for <hi>Preventing the Export<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Corn to</hi> France, and <hi>Ruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Price of it at home,</hi> and for the <hi>ſetling Poor People on Work.</hi> For indeed, the <hi>French</hi> Provinces, by reaſon of the Scarcity of <hi>Corn,</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:154343:71"/>were in great ſtraits, and the <hi>French</hi> King uſed all poſſible means to draw it out of other Kingdoms, to prevent the Encroaching Famine; notwithſtanding which, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments he met withal a great many of his Subjects Miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly periſhed by Hunger, whilſt that King exacted by an Arbitrary way, their <hi>Corn</hi> and other Proviſions from them, to lay up his Stores, and Supply his <hi>Magazines</hi> on the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers.</p>
            <p>AND the King (after the cloſe of the <hi>Campaign,</hi> and his having Eſcaped very great Dangers, and Signalized his Courage to his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Glory, at the Battle of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi>) returning to <hi>England</hi> that God might ſtill continue his Mercys and Favours towards us: A Day of Publick <hi>Thankſgiving</hi> was ſet apart by Their <hi>Majeſtys</hi> Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, bearing Date the Second of <hi>November,</hi> 1693. Which was very Religiouſly and Devoutly Obſerved,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:154343:72"/>through the Kingdom on the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Days. And the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> and Court of <hi>Aldermen,</hi> waited on Their Majeſties to Congratulate His Majeſty's Happy Return, and His Wonderful Preſervation in that Signal Providence, that had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected him in the greateſt of Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to which he had expoſed his Royal Perſon for our ſafety; and all the Nation Sympathiz'd with them, in their <hi>Joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>Winter</hi> was chiefly paſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in great <hi>Preparations</hi> by <hi>Sea &amp; Land,</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> chearfully gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Their <hi>Majeſties</hi> thoſe <hi>Supplys</hi> that were <hi>Neceſſary</hi> for the carrying on a <hi>War,</hi> promiſing <hi>Succeſs &amp; Safety,</hi> to the moſt <hi>Significant Kingdoms &amp; states of Europe:</hi> And early in the <hi>Spring,</hi> the <hi>Turkey and Streights Fleet</hi> again ſet forward on their <hi>Voyage,</hi> but met with ſome diſappointments in the <hi>Streights,</hi> by <hi>Streſs of Weather:</hi> And now Admiral <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> taking a Second time his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> which the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:154343:72"/>the laſt <hi>Year</hi> was in the the Hands of 3 <hi>Admirals joyntly.</hi> The <hi>Fleet</hi> haſtned to <hi>Sea,</hi> and got out ſo Early, that the <hi>French</hi> found a main diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the repeated loſſes they ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: A great many of their <hi>Corn Ships,</hi> &amp; thoſe with <hi>Noval Stores</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken by ours. And the <hi>Kings</hi> intent upon the great Affairs abroad the <hi>3d</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 1694 left <hi>Witehall,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd by the <hi>Queen,</hi> who having taken her leave of him, ſoon after <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued</hi> for <hi>Holland,</hi> and after receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the uſual <hi>Complements,</hi> paſſed to the <hi>Campaign,</hi> finding all things in a very early readineſs, and a poſture promiſing Succeſs.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Navy Royal</hi> having been out ſome time in the <hi>Narrow Seas,</hi> &amp; no <hi>Enemy</hi> daring to appear, <hi>Admiral Ruſſel</hi> with the greater part of ours, and the <hi>Dutch Squadron,</hi> had Orders to Sail to the <hi>Streights,</hi> and in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the <hi>Spaniſh Ships of War and Gallys,</hi> prevent the Deſigns the <hi>French</hi> had on the Coaſts of <hi>Catolonia,</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:154343:73"/>whoſe unexpected coming put <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Tourville,</hi> the <hi>French Admiral,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch apprehenſions of danger, that inſtead of adventuring to <hi>Engage</hi> us, or <hi>Beſiege Barcelonia</hi> by <hi>Sea,</hi> or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept our <hi>Streights &amp; Turkey Fleet,</hi> he ordered his <hi>Ships</hi> into the <hi>Harbour</hi> before <hi>Toulon,</hi> barring up as well as he could the <hi>Haven,</hi> and making <hi>Platforms</hi> on <hi>Shoar</hi> to defend it; and at laſt Diſarmed his <hi>Capital Men of War,</hi> and ſent a great part of the <hi>Seamen</hi> over land to <hi>Breſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHILST theſe Succeſſes happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed further off, a Terrour and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation was brought on the <hi>Coaſt</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> oppoſite to our Shoar, for the Lord <hi>Berkly</hi> keeping the Narrow <hi>Seas,</hi> with a ſtrong <hi>Squadron</hi> Entred the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Diep,</hi> Bomb'd that <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Town,</hi> and lay'd it in Ruins, and afterward, had almoſt the like Succeſs at <hi>Havre de Grace;</hi> putting a great many Stately <hi>Buildings</hi> in <hi>Elames,</hi> which brought ſuch a terror on the people, that many on the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:154343:73"/>
               <hi>Coaſt</hi> left their Habitations: And <hi>Dunkirk</hi> was likewiſe Attempted, but by reaſon of the badneſs of the <hi>Harbour</hi> for <hi>Entrance</hi> and <hi>Weather,</hi> we could not there have the like ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Confederates</hi> during theſe Tranſactions, preſſed the <hi>French Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys</hi> in <hi>Savoy,</hi> upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and in <hi>Flanders:</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a ſhameful Retreat in <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> and the <hi>Tartars</hi> that came to Relieve <hi>Caminick,</hi> were Routed by the <hi>Poles: Huy</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the <hi>French;</hi> and their Boaſted Reſolutions appeared every where, to be in the Declining Scale, ſo that the <hi>Campaign</hi> ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ending on the part of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates</hi> by <hi>Land,</hi> &amp; our <hi>Grand Fleet</hi> ſtill keeping their ſtation, for <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in the Spaniſh Ports.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> having received the <hi>Complements</hi> and <hi>Thanks</hi> of the <hi>States General &amp;c.</hi> Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>England,</hi> was met by the <hi>Queen,</hi> with Unexpreſſible Joy;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:154343:74"/>and the <hi>Cities</hi> of <hi>London &amp; Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> in the <hi>Evening,</hi> as they came to <hi>Town,</hi> were filled with Illuminations, <hi>Bonfires</hi> were made, and the <hi>Bells Tuned</hi> to the <hi>Muſick</hi> of the Peoples Joyful <hi>Acclamation;</hi> and through theſe <hi>Demonſtrations</hi> of <hi>Gratitude &amp; Loyalty,</hi> the Royal Pair paſſed to <hi>Kenſington,</hi> where they were waited on by the <hi>Nobility,</hi> with a <hi>Tender</hi> of their Humbly Duty, and ſoon after the <hi>King</hi> was Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly Pleaſed to tell the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in his Speech, <hi>Of the ſtop that had been this Year put to the Torrent of the</hi> French <hi>Proceedings, which had altogether put them to a ſtand and was a Happy Omen of future ſucceſs; and that nothing might be wanting on his part, to Oblige his Loving Subjects.</hi> An Act was paſſed for the <hi>Frequent meeting of Parliaments,</hi> to the high Satisfaction of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT whilſt theſe Occaſions of <hi>Joy Brightned</hi> in the <hi>Countenance</hi> of all the Well Affected People of theſe
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:154343:74"/>
               <hi>Kingdoms.</hi> A Sad and <hi>Melancholy Cloud</hi> of <hi>Sorrow</hi> too ſudainly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowed our Rejoycings with <hi>Grief</hi> and <hi>Fear,</hi> upon the News of the <hi>Queens Illneſs,</hi> which begun on the <hi>22d</hi> of <hi>December;</hi> and in a little time Her <hi>Diſtemper</hi> was known to be the <hi>Small Pox,</hi> an Inexorable and Pittyleſs Diſtemper, too to Fatal to the <hi>Royal Family.</hi> And upon this occaſion, that God in his Infinite Mercy would be pleaſed to Preſerve her Life, and Reſtore her Health Publick and Private Prayers were put up.</p>
            <p>BUT what ſhall we ſay, for our Sins, our Sighs and Tears had not an expected return of our fervent wiſhes and deſires; the Bleſſing was too great for us, and Heaven be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved us of it, to change her Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Diadem into a Crown of Stars and Glory: For notwithſtanding all that Art, and the Prayers of a Mourning Nation could do, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Diſtemper put a Period to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:154343:75"/>her pretious Life, on the <hi>28th.</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> in the <hi>33d.</hi> Year of her Age, at her Pallace of <hi>Kenſington;</hi> where ſhe Dyed amidſt the Sighs and Tears of thoſe that were about her, with that Pious Courage and Conſtancy that had attended all the Actions of her Life. For whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable loſs, no valuable things, on this ſide Heaven, can ſuffice to allay our Sorrows, in being depriv'd of the beſt of <hi>Queens,</hi> and of <hi>Women,</hi> in the bloom of her Beauty, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Virtue, and prime of her Years.</p>
            <p>AND whilſt preparations, of ſolemn Pomp and State, were mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for the diſpoſing of her Body in the repoſitory of the Grave, amongſt her Royal Anceſtors, till in the bright Morning of the Reſurrection, it ſhall re-unite with her Angelick Soul in endleſs felicity, the Nations Grief ſwell'd in its higheſt Tide. No Loſs ever came ſo near the Hearts of an Afflicted People, to tranſport them
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:154343:75"/>beyond moderation in Sorrow.</p>
            <p>THE Nations Genious, upon this great Blow, put on the deepeſt of Melancholly; and things appeared as if all Nature Sighed for our Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reperable and Ineſtimable Loſs, ſuch a one as even Poſterity and Ages to come muſt in ſadneſs and regret deplore.</p>
            <p>HIS Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> Earl Marſhal of <hi>England,</hi> purſuant to an Order of <hi>Council,</hi> hereupon put forth his Order, Requiring, as it was expected, all Perſons to go into the deepeſt Mourning; and that the Nobility, &amp;c. ſhould cover their Coaches with Black Cloath, and their Liverys to be of the ſame; which was readily, and with all i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginable complying willingneſs, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed and Obſerved. The Peers and Commons in <hi>Parliament,</hi> weight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the <hi>King,</hi> at <hi>Kenſington</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole this great Loſs, in two Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſeting forth extraordinary Expreſſions of their Sorrow, and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:154343:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>the deep ſenſe they had of the Death of the moſt Pious and Beſt of <hi>Queens;</hi> and to Entreat His Majeſty to moderate his Grief, &amp;c. With proteſtations to ſtand by him againſt all his Enemys abroad and at home.</p>
            <p>THE Loyal City of <hi>London,</hi> in the like manner, expreſs'd its ſadneſs, in a Condolement of ſo general a loſs, as did many other chief places in <hi>England</hi> in their <hi>Addreſſes,</hi> which were received with very Gracious Anſwers. And Mourning <hi>Scotland</hi> beſides its other Demonſtrations of a deep ſenſe of Sorrow Ordered a Day of <hi>Humiliation,</hi> and <hi>Faſting</hi> on the Occaſion,</p>
            <p>Into the Cloſet of the Royal Mourner, Awe and Diſtance Commands us not to Pry, no Pen or Words being capable of uttering or framing ſo much as an <hi>Idea</hi> of the unexpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble grief that reſided there, and therefore all we can do, is to paſs it over in Duteous ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and only add our Earneſt Prayers and Wiſh, <hi>That God of His Infinite Mercy would Support Him with Comforts and Bleſſings, under ſo Weighty Affliction, to be the Protector, Bleſſing, &amp; Comfort of his Sorrowful Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:76"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:77"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154343:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
